<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
<esp:name>Core config</esp:name>
<esp:title>Core Configuration Options</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>

<p class="firstpara">The core elements required for all projects, are:</p>
<ul>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="h_n">n</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="h_name">name</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="h_abbrev">abbrev</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="h_type">type</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="h_logo">logo</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="h_public">public</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="h_blurb">blurb</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="h_image">image</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="h_image-alt">image-alt</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="h_url">url</esp:link></li>
</ul>

 <esp:h>n</esp:h> 
<p>The basename of the project as used in directories, e.g., <code>epsd2</code>.
For subprojects this includes the parent projects separated by slashes, e.g., <code>epsd2/late</code>. This parameter is set when the project is created and cannot be altered without consultation with your project liaison. This should be the first line of your config file. E.g.,</p>
<pre class="example">&lt;project n="cams/gkab"></pre>


  <esp:h>name</esp:h> 
 <p>The  long, human-readable name of the project is not restricted in the same way as
 the abbreviated name and the project name itself. You can edit this as you like. E.g.,</p>
       <pre class="example">&lt;name>electronic Pennsylvania Sumerian Dictionary&lt;/name></pre>
 
  <esp:h>abbrev</esp:h>
 <p>The human-readable abbreviation for the project should be a single word, which can
 mix case, like <code>ePSD</code>. E.g., </p>
    <pre class="example">&lt;abbrev>DCCLT</pre> 
 

  <esp:h>type</esp:h>
 <p>Oracc recognizes several different project types which affect things
     like how the default home page is constructed, and how the pager
     formats a browsable view of the project data.  This parameter is 
    set when the project is created and cannot be altered without 
 consultation with your project liaison. The options are:</p>
 <dl>
    <dt>Project is primarily a corpus (default)</dt>
       <dd><pre class="cookbook">&lt;type>corpus&lt;/type> </pre></dd> 
       <dt>project is primarily a glossary</dt>
        <dd><pre class="cookbook">&lt;type>glossary&lt;/type> </pre></dd> 
      <dt>project is a portal providing only content-pages</dt>
       <dd><pre class="cookbook">&lt;type>portal&lt;/type> </pre></dd> 
       <dt>project is primarily a signlist</dt>
        <dd><pre class="cookbook">&lt;type>signlist&lt;/type> </pre></dd> 
 </dl>
 
  <esp:h>logo</esp:h>
   <p>The text logo to display in the top left corner of the page, e.g.,</p>
  <pre class="example">&lt;logo type="text">corpusdcclt&lt;/logo> </pre>
           
  <esp:h>public</esp:h>
   <p>This parameter makes the project public and includes it in Oracc search, etc. It should not be altered without consultation with your project liaison. The options are:</p>
   <pre class="cookbook">&lt;public>yes&lt;/public> </pre>
   <p>or</p>
    <pre class="cookbook">&lt;public>no&lt;/public> </pre> 
    

  <esp:h>blurb</esp:h>
<p>You have 40 words, about 300 characters including spaces, to give
the most interesting and relevant information about your project,
which is used in the Oracc project list.</p>

<p>Do not repeat the title and abbreviation, because that
is already in the heading. You may include links in the blurb using the HTML tag &lt;a href="..."> --they
do not count against your word or character limit.</p>

<p>If you want split your blurb into two or more paragraphs, each
paragraph must start with a &lt;p> tag and end with a &lt;/p> tag. E.g.,</p>  

<pre class="example">&lt;blurb>&lt;p>Editions and translations of lexical texts (word lists and sign lists) from all periods of cuneiform writing.&lt;/p><br/>
&lt;p>Project directed by Niek Veldhuis at UC Berkeley and supported by the 
&lt;a href="http://www.neh.gov">National Endowment for the Humanities&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>&lt;/blurb></pre>

 <esp:h>image</esp:h>
<p>This image accompanies the blurb. It is always scaled to 320 x 240
pixels (i.e., a 4:3 ratio), so should be chosen with this
constraint in mind. It does not need to be an image that is used
 elsewhere in the project, but it must be placed in the <code>00web/images</code>
directory and given the name <code>thumb.png</code> or <code>thumb.jpg</code>.</p>

<p>Please scale your images so that they are a reasonable size: images
over 100K in size will be rejected by the system. The best format
is <code>.png</code>, but <code>.jpg files are also acceptable.</code></p>

<p>Please try not to use pictures of tablets! For some projects, that
may be inevitable, but since we have so many pictures of tablets in
so many places, it is more interesting to promote your project with
 a scene of relevance either to the context of the work you are
 doing or to the content of the tablets. If you do use a tablet
 image, please choose a relevant section of a relevant text, and
 present something that is meaningful to those able to read it. The section presented should be scaled and processed so that it is
 clearly readable online.</p>
    <pre class="example">&lt;image>thumb.png&lt;image></pre>

  <esp:h>image-alt</esp:h> 
    <p>When the image is displayed online it is accompanied by
    a short description which is used by browsers which do not
    display the image.  This alternative text is required.</p>

  <p>The text should be brief but descriptive--the project 
  list has a number of examples of good practice.  In general, 
  the image content, its provenance and date are a good starting 
  point.</p>
    <pre class="example">&lt;image-alt>Drawing of a list of vessels from Archaic Uruk, circa 3500 BCE&lt;/image-alt></pre>

      <esp:h>url</esp:h>
<p>Projects may be integrated on the Oracc server or they may be
separated, with the portal content on another server and only 
the corpus on the Oracc server.  For the latter type of project, 
this element gives the address of the portal-server.</p>

<pre class="example">&lt;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/sargon&lt;</pre>

<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<p><esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/></p>


</body></html></esp:page>
