<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
<esp:name>Web colours</esp:name>
<esp:title>Website Colours</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>
<p class="firstpara">Colourization of the pager display on your project's website is facilitated by a simple
configuration file and a special rebuild option. This page describes how to set and change those colours.</p>


<p><esp:link bookmark="h_generalprinciples">General principles</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_colourdefinitions">Colour definitions</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_colourbindings">Colour bindings</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_colourdefaults">Colour
defaults</esp:link> </p>

<esp:h>General principles</esp:h>
<p>The colours of your project website are given in the file
<code>00lib/p3colours.txt</code>, which you can open and edit with
<esp:link page="emacs">Emacs</esp:link>. First, choose your colour
palate with the <esp:link bookmark="h_colourdefinitions">colour
definitions</esp:link> options. Then decide which colours to associate
with each element of your portal and/or corpus with the <esp:link
bookmark="h_colourbindings">colour bindings</esp:link> options.</p>

<p>Here is a sample <code>p3colours.txt</code> file:</p>

<pre class="example">
colour-def-dark   	#333366
colour-def-mid   	#777b9d
colour-def-light   	#ffcc00
colour-def-very-light  	#fefefe
colour-def-bright 	#33627d
colour-def-pale  	#ffcc00
colour-def-gray	#3c3c3c

colour-bind-dark	banner-bg 
colour-bind-mid 	border bborder
colour-bind-light	banner-fg heading-bg
colour-bind-very-light  
colour-bind-bright 	hover-bg
colour-bind-pale	hover-fg
colour-bind-gray    heading-fg href-fg
</pre>

<p>The colours of some elements are set to defaults. These are listed
<esp:link bookmark="h_colourdefaults">at the end of this page</esp:link>.</p>

<p>You can update the colours any time you change
the colour configuration simply by <esp:link page="the-oracc-command">saying</esp:link>:</p>

<pre class="cookbook">
oracc colours</pre>

<p>Then you need to reload the page you are viewing in your
browser.</p>

<esp:h>Colour definitions</esp:h>
<p>Each project may use a palate of up to seven different colours. You
do not need to use all seven but you will find it helpful to use at
least four, or your website will be difficult for visitors to use.</p>

<p>As
you can see from the sample file above, each colour definition is
entered on a single line. The first part specifies the type of colour
— dark, mid, light, very light, bright, pale and grey —
in the format, e.g., <code
class="example">colour-def-very-light</code>. Then there is white
space followed by a hashmark and three or six digits, the HTML/CSS notation for
colours. 
</p>

<p> In this scheme,
<code>#fff</code> (or <code>#ffffff</code>) is white;
<code>#000</code> (or <code>#000000</code>) is black.  There are
several colourr maps and wheels on the web, of which one of the nicer
examples is <esp:link url="http://ficml.org/jemimap/style/color/wheel.html">Jemima
Pereira's</esp:link> which is also locally cached on <esp:link url="/doc/downloads/jemimap/wheel.html">the
Oracc server</esp:link>.</p>


<esp:h>Colour bindings</esp:h>
<p>Once you have chosen the colour palette, you then need to decide
which elements of your website will use each colour. Again, there are
up to seven lines, one for each colour. But instead of the hexadecimal
colour
codes, you specify the element(s) to be coloured. These are listed below. </p>

<p>Colour specification for regions is always done in pairs, with both
text/foreground (<code>-fg</code>) and background (<code>-bg</code>)
elements being required.  Border colours are given as singletons.</p>


<esp:sh>Region colours</esp:sh>
<dl>
<dt>logo-fg logo-bg</dt>
<dd>Colours for the logo patch in the top left corner of the pager display.</dd>

<dt>banner-fg banner-bg</dt>
<dd>Colours for the banner across the top of the pager
display. Defaults to the same as the logo colours.</dd>

<dt>banner-borders</dt>
<dd>Colour for the banner borders.</dd>

<dt>other-borders</dt>
<dd>Colour for all borders except the banner.</dd>

<dt>alt-fg alt-bg</dt>
<dd>Alternative colours which are used for example in the headings the
pager uses for text titles and for the outline-based headings that
come between lists of paged items and references.</dd>

<dt>h3-fg h3-bg</dt>
<dd>Colours for HTML H3 headings; presently only used in the metadata
panel of a text display.</dd>
</dl>

<esp:sh>Link Colours</esp:sh>

<p>Links may involve six colour specifications because they have
foreground and background for unvisited, visited and hover states.
Each link set name described below thus expands to six options, formed
on the pattern <code class="example">NAME-STATE-FGBG</code>.  The name
<code>logo</code> implies the existence of <code class="cookbook">logo-unvisited-bg logo-unvisited-fg logo-visited-bg
logo-visited-fg logo-hover-bg logo-hover-fg</code>.</p>

<dl>
<dt>logo</dt>
<dd>Links in the logo.</dd>

<dt>banner</dt>
<dd>Links in the banner.</dd>

<dt>alt</dt>
<dd>Links when the background is the alternative colour.</dd>

<dt>lemm</dt>
<dd>Links from lemmatized words in texts.</dd>

<dt>score</dt>
<dd>Links from the numbers in a composite text to the score blocks.</dd>
</dl>

<esp:h>Colour defaults</esp:h>
<p>There are some elements that are coloured consistently across
Oracc. You cannot change them within a project. The most important of theses are as
follows:</p>

<dl>
  <dt>page: #ffffff</dt>
  <dd>Page backgrounds are always white.</dd>
  <dt>text: #000000</dt>
  <dd>Main text is always  black.</dd>
  <dt>PGP and Techterms links: #333333</dt>
  <dd>In portal pages, lines surrounding links to entries in People,
  Gods and Places and Technical Terms lists are always light
  grey.</dd>
  
</dl>



<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>


</body></html></esp:page>
