<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>


<esp:name>Lemmatising</esp:name>
<esp:title>Lemmatising ATF Files</esp:title><html><head/>

<body><p class="firstpara">Lemmatisation consists of labelling written words, which may be inflected, with the base word (or dictionary headword) of which the written form is an instance. Oracc's lemmatiser, L2, helps you generate glossaries from your Oracc corpus.</p>

<esp:sh>Learning and Using L2</esp:sh>
<dl>
<dt><esp:link page="linganno">Lemmatisation Primer</esp:link></dt>
<dd>This page provides an introduction to linguistic annotation facilities, especially lemmatization, used in Oracc.</dd>
<dt><esp:link page="howtouseit">Lemmatising: How to Use L2</esp:link></dt>
<dd>This page summarises the steps required to use L2, the lemmatiser used by Oracc. First we describe what you need to know about editing ATF files, then glossary management, then rebuilding the whole project. This page is designed as a refresher for those already familiar with lemmatisation.</dd>
<dt><esp:link page="languages">Languages</esp:link></dt>
<dd>More details on lemmatising <esp:link page="akk-anno">Akkadian</esp:link>, <esp:link page="sux-anno">Sumerian</esp:link>, <esp:link page="qpn-anno">proper nouns</esp:link> and other ancient languages.</dd>
</dl>

<esp:sh>Further details</esp:sh>

<dl>
<dt><esp:link page="cofs">COFs: Compound Orthographic Forms</esp:link></dt>
<dd>This page describes how the lemmatiser handles Compound Orthographic Forms, or written words which contain more than one lemma.</dd>
<dt><esp:link page="psus">PSUs: Phrasal Semantic Units</esp:link></dt>
<dd>This page describes how L2 handles Phrasal Semantic Units, or glossary entries which consist of more than one word.</dd>
<dt><esp:link page="bffs">BFFs: Byforms</esp:link></dt>
<dd>BFFs are the Oracc glossary mechanism for word byforms of various kinds. The general mechanism allows the individual byforms to be treated under their own entries within the glossary and during lemmatization, but then be kept separate or grouped together when the glossaries are rendered.</dd>
<dt><esp:link page="errors">Rebuild Errors</esp:link></dt>
<dd>This page gives some help with fixing rebuild error messages that arise through lemmatisation or glossary management problems.</dd>
</dl>


<esp:sh>More technical descriptions</esp:sh>
<dl>
<dt><esp:link page="howitworks">L2: How It Works</esp:link></dt>
<dd>This document provides an overview of how the lemmatizer, L2, works to help Oracc builders understand what files are used for validation and how to control lemmatization.</dd>
<dt><esp:link page="lemsyntax">L2: Signature/Lemmatization Syntax</esp:link></dt>
<dd>This document describes extant and planned elements of the syntax of signatures and the lemmatization specifications that use them.</dd>
<dt></dt>
</dl>
<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>
</body></html></esp:page>
