<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
<esp:name>Signatures</esp:name>
<esp:title>Signatures</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>

<p>Signatures are the string representation of an instance's
lemmatization data and consists of a sequence of fields, each
introduced by a distinct prefix character or characters. A complete
signature looks like this:</p>

<pre class="cookbook">@epsd2%sux:a=a[water//water]N'N/a#~$a</pre>

<p>Abbreviated Signatures</p>

<p>Oracc's lemmatization allows users to enter just a few key pieces
of a signature (this is the "instance lemmatization") and the
lemmatizer looks this data up in the glossary and creates complete
signatures from it.</p>

<p>Users typically enter just the citation form (CF, a in the example
above) and the sense (SENSE, water above), and the instance
lemmatization is then <code class="example">a[water]</code>.  It is
also not uncommon to give simply a Part-of-Speech, such as <code
class="example">PN</code>, for the instance lemmatization.</p>

<p>Signature Fields and Prefix Characters</p>

<dl>
  <dt>@ = PROJECT</dt><dd>The project to which this signature belongs</dd>
  <dt>% = LANG</dt><dd>The language for the signature; may also have a writing system, e.g., %akk-949 for normalized Akkadian</dd>
  <dt>: = FORM</dt><dd>The form of the word as it appears in the text</dd>
  <dt>= = CF</dt><dd>The = separates FORM and CF, or Citation Form; the equals may be omitted if the CF is the first entry in the signature, as in a[water]</dd>
  <dt>[ ... ]</dt><dd>Square brackets surround the GW, or Guide Word, and/or SENSE</dd>
  <dt>//</dt><dd>Only within [...], the double slash // separates GW and SENSE</dd>
  <dt>POS</dt><dd>The POS (Part-of-Speech) is identified by its position immediately after the closing square bracket of [...]</dd>
  <dt>' = EPOS</dt><dd>The right-quote, ', is the prefix character for the EPOS, the Effective Part-of-Speech</dd>
  <dt>$ = NORM</dt>
  <dd>The normalized version of the writing. This varies by
  language: in Akkadian, for example, it is the transcription of
  the word-form, without hyphens and determinatives and with
  accents. This is not used in the source version of Sumerian
  glossaries because it can be computed from the morphology (see
  below).</dd>
  <dt>* = STEM</dt>
  <dd>The STEM, which may be a form of the BASE in Sumerian, or a
  notation such as D, Š, N, in Akkadian, or possibly other
  conventions for other languages.</dd>
  <dt>/ = BASE</dt>
  <dd>The BASE utilized in a Sumerian writing. This must match a
  base given in the <code>@bases</code> part of the entry.</dd>
  <dt>+ = CONT</dt>
  <dd>The Sumerian grapheme following the base, used only when that
  grapheme is the continuation of the end of the BASE,
  e.g., <code>-ma</code> in <code>inim-ma</code>.  The
  deconstruction of the grapheme gives the consonant which
  continues the grapheme followed by the vowel which is normally a
  morpheme or morpheme constituent.</dd>
  <dt># = MORPH</dt>
  <dd>The morphology string for the writing.</dd>
  <dt>## = MORPH2</dt>
  <dd>The second morphology string for the writing.</dd>
  <dt>@ = RWS</dt>
  <dd>The RWS, Register or Writing System, for the form.</dd>
</dl>

</body>
</html>
</esp:page>
