<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>


	<esp:name>Contributing</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Contributing to Oracc</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>
<p class="firstpara">On this page we explain the various ways of participating in
project-building with Oracc and what it means to contribute texts
following either of our two models: <esp:link bookmark="h_donation">donation</esp:link> and <esp:link bookmark="h_curation">curation</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:sh>Donation</esp:sh>

<p>Under the donation model, you simply send us your text
editions — which may include additional information like translations,
prosopographies, etc. — and we take care of installing them on Oracc and
maintaining them.  We may ask you to review the results of our
conversion processes to ensure that the material that goes online is
representative of your work, but after that we may edit it as
necessary to interoperate smoothly with other Oracc corpora.  Note that
it is not our policy to introduce arbitrary or unnecessary edits
(quite apart from anything else we have many other things to do), but
we may make changes following collation or further research in the
field.</p>

<p>We will identify you as the source of the data, and indicate the
identity of subsequent revisers of the data as necessary.</p>

<esp:sh>Curation</esp:sh>

<p>Under the curation model, we will help you set up your texts as a
separate project or subproject on the Oracc server.  We will look to you
to lemmatize and maintain the texts, and to develop appropriate educational 'portal' material about them. You will retain greater
control over subsequent edits.</p>

<p>Because the Oracc software is well-suited to the development of
corpora, and because a corpus or a portal can be transformed into a book, we hope
that people will find it advantageous to begin projects under the
curation model even if they later feel that it is better ultimately to
donate their texts, perhaps after the publication of the book, or when
their research interests shift.</p>

<p>We welcome inquiries about planning new projects at any time. You
do not need specialist computer skills to run an Oracc project. We can
assist with all aspects of the process, from grant-writing onwards. In
fact the earlier you consult us, the more we can help. Please email us
at <esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/> to tell us more about your interests and needs.</p>

<esp:sh>Implications</esp:sh>

<p>Our policy is that all material in Oracc is available for
re-use under a <esp:link page="licensing">Creative
Commons Attribution Share-Alike license</esp:link>. That means, in practice,
that anybody can download texts, change them and publish them again as
long as the source is mentioned and the new work is released under the
same (or similar) license.</p>

<p>As the size of the Oracc user base grows, there is an increasing
likelihood that something like that will indeed happen. For example,
someone who is working on a project about some aspect of Mesopotamian
culture may need to prepare editions of texts which have
special-purpose annotation and then may well use your text, or another
project's version of it, as her point of departure.  For us, this
ability to build on the work of others — always crediting them for
their contributions — is a key reason for the implementation of the Oracc
system and a major factor in our willingness to invest large amounts
of time in the project.</p>

<esp:sh>More Information</esp:sh>

<p>To read more introductory information about Oracc you can go
to <esp:link page="howandwhy">the How and Why page</esp:link>.  If you have
further questions or would like to donate or curate texts, you can
e-mail us at <esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>.</p>

<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>
	</body></html>

</esp:page>
