<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>


	<esp:name>About Oracc</esp:name>
	<esp:title>About Oracc</esp:title>
	<html><head></head><body>
<p class="firstpara">The Open Richly Annotated Cuneiform Corpus (Oracc) is an international
cooperative which provides facilities and support for the creation of
free online editions of cuneiform texts and educational 'portal' websites about ancient cuneiform culture.</p> 

<p><esp:link bookmark="h_licensing">Licensing</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_history">History</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_methods">Methods</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_steeringcommittee">Steering Committee</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_liaisons">Liaisons</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_hosting">Hosting</esp:link></p>

<esp:sh>Licensing</esp:sh>
<p>Because we believe that the
free reusability of data is essential for scholarly progress, we
strongly recommend the use of <esp:link url="http://creativecommons.org/about" rel="external">Creative Commons</esp:link> licensing for Oracc projects, and by
default Oracc projects are placed under the CC <esp:link url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" rel="external">"Attribution
Share-Alike"</esp:link> license. Read more about Oracc's licensing <esp:link page="licensing">here</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:sh>History</esp:sh>
<p>Oracc emerged from <esp:link url="http://cdli.ucla.edu" rel="external">The Cuneiform
Digital Library Initiative</esp:link> (CDLI). Oracc is a natural complement to
CDLI's central archival role as a catalogue and image database of the
entire cuneiform corpus and a repository for reference
transliterations of that corpus. Oracc transliterations are
automatically supplied to the CDLI repository.</p>

<esp:sh>Methods</esp:sh>
<p>Oracc enables groups of texts to be sliced out of the entire corpus
and studied intensively within what we call &#x2018;projects&#x2019;. A project&#x2019;s
functions can include building signlists, glossaries and
prosopographies of these subcorpora. Multilingual translation support
is built in to the system, and projects can be turned into Word files,
PDFs, and books using the ISO <esp:link rel="external" url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenDocument">OpenDocument</esp:link> standard. Project data can also be
exported to the data format defined by the <esp:link rel="external" url="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml">Text Encoding Initiative</esp:link>. TEI export may be used by external
projects for further analysis.</p>

<esp:sh>Steering Committee</esp:sh>
<p>The Oracc Steering Committee (OSC) currently comprises
<esp:link rel="external" url="http://www.ag.geschichte.uni-muenchen.de/personen/mitarbeiter/novotny/index.html">Jamie
Novotny</esp:link> at LMU Munich,
<esp:link rel="external" url="http://www.hps.cam.ac.uk/people/robson/">Eleanor
Robson</esp:link> at the University of Cambridge,
<esp:link rel="external" url="http://ccat.sas.upenn.edu/anch/faculty/tinney.htm">Steve
Tinney</esp:link> at the University of Pennsylvania, and
<esp:link rel="external" url="http://www.ocf.berkeley.edu/~veldhuis/">Niek
Veldhuis</esp:link> at the University of California Berkeley.
The OSC is responsible for ensuring the continuity and documentation
of the Oracc system and its permanent web presence, and for assisting
with the creation and maintenance of projects. The committee is
non-hierarchical and all of its members have equal status.</p>

<esp:sh>Liaisons</esp:sh>
<p>In general, Oracc projects have one OSC member assigned to them as
the Oracc liaison. We are here to help set up and develop projects. For
new projects we can provide technical appendices for inclusion in
grant applications and other input and feedback into that process as
requested.</p>

<esp:sh>Hosting</esp:sh>
<p>For ongoing or completed projects using other systems, and for
individuals who would like to put their text editions permanently
online, we can provide help with converting the text editions to our
standards and putting them on the web. Contributors can simply pass
their work on to us and have no further involvement, or they are
always welcome to continue working with their material under the Oracc
umbrella and become managers of their own project.</p>

<p>For more details, see the page on <esp:link page="contributing">Contributing Corpora</esp:link> to Oracc.</p>

<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>

	</body></html>

</esp:page>
