<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
  <esp:name>Composites</esp:name>
    <esp:title>ATF Composites Conventions</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>
    <p class="firstpara">This document describes ATF features which are available when
    entering composite texts.</p>

<p>Composite texts by convention have an ID beginning with Q and are
declared by an @-line which immediately follows the &amp;-line for the
text:</p>
<pre class="cookbook">
&amp;Q000002 = Archaic Lu A
@composite</pre>

<p>Composite IDs are listed in the <esp:link url="http://oracc.museum.upenn.edu/qcat">Oracc Qcat</esp:link>. To obtain an ID for a composite text email <esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>.</p>

<esp:h>Structure</esp:h>

<p>Most of the @-lines which are permitted in transliterations are not
permitted in composites; this is because composites are organized
around documentary structure rather than the structure of a physical
object.  The one exception is that milestones are allowed in
composites.</p>

<p>Documentary divisions are indicated in ATF by use of the
<code>@div</code> tag which is followed by the name of the division
and an optional name for the division.  The <code>@div</code> tag
requires a closing <code>@end</code> tag, which must take as its
single argument the name of its corresponding opening
<code>@div</code>.  <code>@div</code>'s of different kinds may not be
interwoven.</p>

<pre class="cookbook"> 
@div part 1
...
@end part

@div colophon
...
@end colophon</pre>

<p>In the liturgical corpus (including ETCSL editions of texts which
could reasonably be considered liturgical), kirugu and other rubrics
are used as logical structures, and they contain subdivisions giving
the actual rubric; this is supported with the following syntax:</p>

<pre class="cookbook">
@div kirugu 1
1.  tur3-ra-na ...

@div rubric kirugu
10. ki-ru-gu2 1(disz)-a-kam
@end rubric

@end kirugu

@div giszgigal 1
11. u2-a a-u3-a u2-a-u2-a

@div rubric giszgigal
12. gisz-gi4-gal2-bi-im
@end rubric

@end giszgigal</pre>

<p>A physical location may be given in a composite by using the
locator milestone; the content after locator is a label.  This is
intended for use when the documentary structure of composites is being
used to edit a text which is preserved only in one exemplar (the ePSD
royal inscriptions corpus edits all royal inscriptions as composites):</p>

<pre class="cookbook">
1. a
@m=locator o 1</pre>

<esp:h>Variants</esp:h>

<p>Variants are implemented to support the ETCSL corpus but may be
used in any composite.</p>

<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>
</body>
</html>
</esp:page>