<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

<esp:name>Labels</esp:name>
<esp:title>Labels</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>

<p class="firstpara">Labels are generated for lines by the ATF processor
  and are used to reference lines in some parts of the ATF system.
  This document describes the syntax of labels.</p>



<esp:h>Overview</esp:h>

<p>Labels are a shorthand way of referring to the location of a line
on an object.  For transliterations, labels consist of at most three
parts: a <code>SURFACE</code> abbreviation, a <code>COLUMN</code>
designation and a <code>LINE</code> number.</p>

<esp:sh>SURFACE</esp:sh>

<p>The <code>SURFACE</code> field is an abbreviation of ATF surface
tags according to the following table:</p>

<table class="pretty">
<thead>
<tr><th>ATF</th><th>LABEL</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>@obverse</td><td>o</td></tr>
<tr><td>@reverse</td><td>r</td></tr>
<tr><td>@bottom</td><td>b.e.</td></tr>
<tr><td>@edge</td><td>e.</td></tr>
<tr><td>@left</td><td>l.e.</td></tr>
<tr><td>@right</td><td>r.e.</td></tr>
<tr><td>@top</td><td>t.e.</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>If the transliteration does not give <code>@obverse</code>
explicitly, labels for line numbers on the obverse do not include the
`o'.</p>

<esp:sh>COLUMN</esp:sh>

<p>Column numbers in labels are rendered in roman numerals, which both
follows normal Assyriological practice and avoids possible confusion
with the line numbers.  This does mean, however, that the notations
for column numbers in ATF sources and labels are different:
<code>@column 1</code> in a label is <code>i</code>.</p>

<p>If the transliteration does not include column number tags, no
column number component is included in the label.</p>

<esp:sh>LINE</esp:sh>

<p>There are two possible line numbers which the ATF processor can use
in labels.  By default, the processor renumbers lines according to
CDLI conventions--restarting line numbers at `1' at the start of each
surface and numbering lines consecutively.  However, in contexts where
stability is required--where the labels are being used to link
exemplar lines to composite lines, for example--the ATF protocol:</p>

<pre class="cookbook">#atf: use mylines
</pre>

<p>should be used.  This instructs the processor to prefer the user's
line numbers to its auto-generated ones.  The line numbers in
transliterations have few restrictions--as long as they consist of a
series of non-spaces followed by a period followed by a space they are
considered acceptable.</p>

<esp:h>Syntax</esp:h>

<esp:sh>LABEL</esp:sh>

<p>Considering the preceding comments and using the convention
<code>?</code> to indicate optional components, the syntax of a single
label is then:</p>

<pre class="example">LABEL =&gt; SURFACE? COLUMN? LINE
</pre>

<esp:sh>LABEL_RANGE</esp:sh>

<p>There is a standard syntax for ranges also, which must be observed
when, e.g., translations use labeling to refer to blocks of
transliteration.  In such cases, two labels may be given and
<strong>must</strong> be separated by the sequence: SPACES HYPHEN
SPACES.  The reason for requiring the spaces is that ATF line numbers
may contain hyphens so we require ranges to include spaces between the
components.</p>

<p>Formally, then, we have the following definition:</p>

<pre class="example">LABEL_RANGE =&gt; LABEL ' - ' LABEL
</pre>

<esp:sh>LABEL_SPEC</esp:sh>

<p>Combining the preceding definitions, we can now define a label
specification, LABEL_SPEC, as follows (using the standard notation of
vertical bar (`|') = OR):</p>

<pre class="example">LABEL_SPEC =&gt; LABEL | LABEL_RANGE
</pre>

<esp:h>Examples</esp:h>

<p>Let the notation <code>@obverse ... @column 1 ... 1.</code> mean
that the ATF transliteration has block tags <code>@obverse</code> and
<code>@column 1</code>, among other possible content, and that
<code>1.</code> is a line number.  Then the following relations
apply:</p>

<table class="pretty">
<thead>
<tr><th>ATF</th><th>LABEL</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>1.</td><td>1</td></tr>
<tr><td>@column 1 ... 1.</td><td>i 1</td></tr>
<tr><td>@obverse ... @column 1 ... 1.</td><td>o i 1</td></tr>
<tr><td>@left ... 3'.</td><td>l.e. 3'</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<esp:h>Related documentation</esp:h>
<ul>
<li><esp:link page="translation" bookmark="sh_labeled">Labeled translations</esp:link></li>
<li><esp:link page="linkage">ATF linkage</esp:link></li>
</ul>

<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>


</body></html></esp:page>
