<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
    <esp:name>Linkage</esp:name>
    <esp:title>ATF Linkage</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>
    <p class="firstpara">This document describes the ATF mechanisms for
    intertext linking.  The original version of this document was
    written by Madeleine Fitzgerald and Steve Tinney.</p>

<p> <esp:link bookmark="h_background">Background</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_operators">Operators</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_targetsandlinkdefinitions">Targets and Link Definitions</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_labels">Labels</esp:link> |
<esp:link bookmark="h_syntax">Syntax</esp:link> | <esp:link
bookmark="h_implementation">Implementation</esp:link> | <esp:link
bookmark="h_examples">Examples</esp:link> </p>

    <esp:h>Background</esp:h>
    
      <p>The ATF format supports inline notations of three relationships
between lines in different texts:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>parallels, in which a line or lines in one text are similar to
lines in another text</li>
        <li>sources, or lines which are being included in a composite text
but originate in other texts</li>
        <li>contributors, or lines which are being entered in a
transliteration and at the same time are relevant to the
reconstruction of a composite text</li>
      </ul>
    
    <esp:h>Operators</esp:h>
    
      <p>Linking composite text lines to lines in individual texts, lines
in exemplars to lines in composite texts, and matching lines in two
or more individual exemplars or composite texts are indicated with
the following notation at the beginning of the next line after the
line of transliterated text to be linked.</p>
      <dl>
        <dt>&lt;&lt;</dt>
        <dd>line comes from tablet instance (source)</dd>
        <dt>&gt;&gt;</dt>
        <dd>line goes to composite text (contributor)</dd>
        <dt>||</dt>
        <dd>before reference to line in parallel composite or tablet
(parallel)</dd>
      </dl>
      <p>The source ('comes from') and contributor ('goes to') facilities
are intended to allow creation of composite texts in the absence of
a complete set of transliterated sources and, conversely, to allow
the transliteration of individual sources by reference to a
composite text which may not yet include the original sources.</p>
      <p>The parallel link facility is especially useful for editing
tablets such as those containing liturgical texts and incantations
where creating a composite text may be practically futile as well
as methodologically dubious.</p>
    
    <esp:h>Targets and Link Definitions</esp:h>
    
      <p>A <code>TARGET</code> is a reference to another text related to
the one at hand. Every linked text must be defined and given a
<code>TARGET</code> identifier in the file in which it is to be
used before the first use; we recommend grouping all the
definitions together just before the <code>&amp;</code>-line (text
ID/name line).</p>
      <p>A linked text definition takes the form:</p>
      <pre>
#link: def linktext &lt;TARGET&gt; = &lt;ID&gt; = &lt;NAME&gt;
</pre>
      <p>For example:</p>
      <pre>
#link: def A =  P227635 = CBS 10792 (OB Syllabary B)
</pre>
      <p>The variable elements of this definition are:</p>
      <dl>
        <dt>TARGET</dt>
        <dd>the name that is used in the link specifiers; this is normally
an uppercase letter, e.g., <code>A</code>, but the only actual
restriction on the spelling of a target is that it may not contain
any whitespace.</dd>
        <dt>ID</dt>
        <dd>the ID as assigned by the CDLI project; for transliterated
objects this begins with a 'P', e.g., P123456. Other text types
have similar identifiers with different initial letters.</dd>
        <dt>NAME</dt>
        <dd>the human-readable name assigned by the CDLI project; in the
XML format this is the value of the 'N' attribute.</dd>
      </dl>
      <p>The ID and NAME values of texts can be obtained from the CDLI
website; for texts which have not yet been assigned ID's, use an
initial 'X' followed by digits as an interim measure and e-mail the
CDLI staff to request IDs (cdli@ucla.edu).</p>
    
    <esp:h>Labels</esp:h>
    
      <p>The target is followed by a label that gives the location of the
related text in the target document. Labels are constructed
according to the following abbreviations (which are designed to be
easy to type while still allowing programmatic reconstruction of
the location of the reference in the XML dataset):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>o = obverse</li>
        <li>r = reverse</li>
        <li>t = top edge</li>
        <li>b = bottom edge</li>
        <li>l = left edge</li>
        <li>r = right edge</li>
        <li>e = edge</li>
        <li>&lt;surface&gt; = other surface, e.g.,
<code>shoulder</code></li>
        <li>face a..z = prism face a to z</li>
        <li>seal n = seal n (n = the number of the seal in the
transliteration)</li>
        <li>&lt;roman&gt; = column number in lowercase roman numerals</li>
        <li>&lt;line number&gt;</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Spaces are required between elements of a label, for example, o
i 2 = obverse, column 1, line 2.</p>
      <p>Two labels, a 'from' label and a 'to' label, are used when there
is a need to indicate a range of text beyond a single line in the
target document. A range requires a hypehn character between the
two labels.</p>
    
    <esp:h>Syntax</esp:h>
    
      <p>The syntax of these constructs is either:</p>
      <pre>
&lt;OPERATOR&gt; &lt;TARGET&gt; &lt;LABEL&gt;</pre>
      <p>or:</p>
      <pre>
&lt;OPERATOR&gt; &lt;TARGET&gt; &lt;FROM_LABEL&gt; - &lt;TO_LABEL&gt;</pre>
    
    <esp:h>Implementation
Notes</esp:h>
    
      <p>A separate program manages the links in such a way that it is
unnecessary to group together all of the links to a specific
parallel. In other words, given three texts which contain the same
parallel, let's say Liturgy 1, 2 and 3, one can encode the
relationship as follows:</p>
      <pre>
@transliteration
#link: def A = P222222 = Liturgy 2
&amp;P111111 = Liturgy 1
1. a-u-a
|| A 1</pre>
      <pre>
&amp;P222222 = Liturgy 2
1. a-u2-a</pre>
      <pre>
#link: def A = P222222 = Liturgy 2
&amp;P333333 = Liturgy 3
1. a-u3-a
|| A 1</pre>
      <p>The link manager will resolve the links in Liturgy 1 and Liturgy
3 and construct a link-ring in which all three parallels refer
mutually to each other. The search engine will automatically
display all parallels whenever a match is found in any of the
lines.</p>
    
    <esp:h>Examples</esp:h>
    
      <p>
        <b>(a) Source (line in composite 'comes from' exemplar):</b>
      </p>
      <p>
        <i>File 1:</i>
      </p>
      <pre>
&amp;P121323 = OB Lu excerpt N 4304
1. lu2</pre>
      <p>
        <i>File 2:</i>
      </p>
      <pre>
@composite
#link: def A = P123123 = OB Lu excerpt N 4304
&amp;Q123238 = A = OB Lu A
1. lu2
&lt;&lt; A 1</pre>
      <p>
        <b>(b) Contributor (line in exemplar 'goes to'
composite)</b>
      </p>
      <p>
        <i>File 1:</i>
      </p>
      <pre>
@composite
&amp;Q123238 = OB Lu A
1. lu2</pre>
      <p>
        <i>File 2:</i>
      </p>
      <pre>
#link: def A = Q128238 = OB Lu A
&amp;P121323 = OB Lu excerpt N 4304
1. A
&gt;&gt;A 1</pre>
      <p>
        <b>(c) Parallel</b>
      </p>
      <p>
        <i>File 1:</i>
      </p>
      <pre>
&amp;P123456 = Kusu Incantation version 1
@reverse
@column 2
1. [am husz gal] du7-du7 gi-[izi-la2] </pre>
      <p>
        <i>File 2:</i>
      </p>
      <pre>
#link: def D = P123456 = Kusu Incantation version 1
&amp;P123457 = Kusu Incantation version 2
1. am husz# gal du7-du7 gi-[izi-la2]
|| D r ii 1</pre>
      <p>The above example shows two exemplars of a text. The second
transliteration contains a definition of the first text as "D" and
indicates that its first line is paralleled (||) in the first line
of the second column of the reverse of the first text. Parallels
may be drawn between composite texts, transliterations or a
combination of the two.</p>



<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>
</body>
</html>
</esp:page>
