<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

<esp:name>Primer</esp:name>
<esp:title>Oracc ATF Primer</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>

<p class="firstpara">A very quick start to get you up and running with
    your first ATF texts by giving some annotated examples.</p>


<esp:h>Example 1</esp:h>
<p>Let's start with an example:</p>


<pre class="cookbook">
&amp;P348865 = SpTU 5, 283
#project: cams
#atf: lang akk-x-ltebab
#atf: use unicode


@tablet

@obverse
1.	ṭup-pi! E₂ ep-šu₂ sip-pu rak-su E₂ rug-gu-bu
2.	{giš}IG SAG.KUL kun-nu KI{+ti₃} {id₂}har ša₂ {d}NA₃
$ single ruling
3.	40?# ina 1 KUŠ₃ US₂ AN.TA {tu₁₅}SI.SA₂ DA E₂ ša₂ 
</pre>

<p>The various ATF features illustrated here are:</p>
<dl>
<dt>The <code>&amp;-line</code></dt>
<dd>Every text begins with an <code>&amp;-line</code> giving the ID
and the text's designation according to the CDLI catalog; if your text
is not yet in the catalog, e-mail cdli@cdli.ucla.edu or osc@oracc.org to get the ID and
designation.</dd>
<dt><code>#project: cams</code></dt>
<dd>It is mandatory that you specify the project that the text belongs to. The ATF file is not valid if this line is omitted, as the #project line sends essential information to the server and is used for validation and lemmatisation. In addition, this line must come before the #atf protocol lines.</dd>
<dt><code>#atf: lang akk-x-stdbab</code></dt>
<dd>You need to specify the main <esp:link page="languages">language and dialect</esp:link> for the text; for Sumerian just
write <code class="cookbook">#atf: lang sux</code>.</dd>
<dt><code>#atf: use unicode</code></dt>
<dd>You can specify that the transliteration is in <esp:link page="visitor-unicode">Unicode</esp:link> (with š, ṣ, ṭ, etc and subscript numerals); if you omit this line then the transliteration must be in ASCII (with sz, s,, and t, and full-size numerals). We strongly recommend that all new ATF files use Unicode for Oracc. <esp:link page="cdli">CDLI ATF</esp:link> continues to use ASCII.</dd>
<dt><code>@tablet</code></dt>
<dd>You can specify an object type; this is normally @tablet, but
others include @bulla and @envelope.</dd>
<dt><code>@obverse, @reverse</code></dt>
<dd>You can specify the part of the object you are transliterating;
the edges are given using: <code class="cookbook">@left @right @top
@bottom</code>.</dd>
<dt>Lines of text</dt>
<dd>Lines of text are for the most part just like regular
Assyriological practice.  See <esp:link bookmark="h_example2">Example 2</esp:link> for how to do breakage.</dd>
<dt>Logograms</dt>
<dd>Logograms can be simply entered as uppercase as is natural in transliterations of Akkadian.</dd>
<dt>Determinatives, phonetic complements and glosses</dt>
<dd><p>Determinatives are given in curly brackets.</p> 
<p>Phonetic complements and glosses are marked with a <code>+</code> immediately after the first curly bracket; they are assumed to be in the same language as the rest of the word.</p> </dd>
<dt>Rulings</dt>
<dd>Lines ruled on the tablet as paragraph separators, etc., can be marked with $-lines ("dollar-lines").</dd>
<dt>Numbers</dt>
<dd>Sexagesimal (base 60) numbers that just use the DIŠ and U signs are transliterated as regular numerals. Numbers in other metrological systems are explicitly qualified as in <code class="cookbook">1(disz)</code>.  See <esp:link page="numbers">the
numbers page</esp:link> and the <esp:link page="math">mathematics page</esp:link> for more information (or the <esp:link page="numbers">numbers and metrology in CDLI page</esp:link> as appropriate).</dd>
</dl>

<p>You can see <esp:link url="http://oracc.museum.upenn.edu/cams/gkab/P348865">here</esp:link> how the entire text appears online in CAMS.</p>
<esp:h>Example 2</esp:h>

<pre class="cookbook">
&amp;P348658 = SpTU 2, 055
#project: cams
#atf: lang akk-x-ltebab
#atf: use unicode


@tablet

@obverse
1.	ṭup-pi A.ŠA₃ ki-šub-ba#-[a ...]
2.	{id₂}har-ri ša₂ {d}MUATI? x [...]
3.	ša₂ qe₂-reb UNUG#[{ki}]
</pre>

<dl>
<dt>Damage and breakage</dt>
<dd><p>There are no half-brackets in ATF: signs which are damaged are
flagged with the hash-sign (<code>#</code>) after the grapheme.</p>
<p>Signs which are completely broken away are placed in square
brackets; square brackets may not occur inside a grapheme, only before
or after it.  The ellipsis (<code>...</code>) may be used to indicate that an
undeterminable number of signs is missing.</p>
<p>Signs which cannot be identified are transliterated as
<code>x</code>; when a number is missing the convention is to use
<code>n</code> as in <code class="cookbook">n(disz)</code>.</p></dd>
<dt>Querying, Correction and Collation</dt>
<dd>The other flags are the query (<code>?</code>) which can be placed
after a grapheme to indicate uncertainty of reading; the asterisk
(<code>*</code>) which indicates a collated reading; and the
exclamation mark which indicates correction.  After a corrected sign,
the actual sign on the tablet may optionally be given: <code class="cookbook">a!</code> or <code class="cookbook">ki!(DI)</code>.</dd>
</dl>

<p>You can see <esp:link url="http://oracc.museum.upenn.edu/cams/gkab/P348658">here</esp:link> how the entire text appears online in CAMS.</p>

<esp:h>Example 3</esp:h>

<p>This shows a Sumerian text with non-sexagesimal numbers, transliterated in ASCII.</p> 
<pre class="cookbook">
&amp;P100099 = AAS 113
#atf: lang sux
@tablet
@obverse
1. 1(ban2) kasz 1(ban2) [...]
2. 1(disz) sila3 [...]
3. 1(u)? [...] gesz
4. 1(barig) kasz#? [...] x [...]
5. 3(ban2) [x]
6. nam-ha-ni sagi
7. {d}gu-la
8. mu-da-gen-na-a
9. iti sze-kar-ra-gal2-la
</pre>

<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>



</body></html></esp:page>
