<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
  <esp:name>Protocols</esp:name>
    <esp:title>ATF Protocols</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>
    <p class="firstpara">This page offers an overview of the protocols
    which may be used in ATF documents.</p>

<p>Protocols are statements which are interpreted or stored by the ATF
processor but are not part of the text edition proper.  Protocols are
all named and may trigger special processing within the ATF
processor.</p>

<p>Protocols are indicated in ATF by a line beginning with the hash
character (<code>#</code>), a known protocol name and a colon character
(<code>:</code>).</p>

<p>With the exception of <code>#note:</code>, protocols must occur on
a single line; multiple protocols do not need blank lines between them
except for multiple <code>#note:</code> protocols which behave like
comments.</p>

<p>Protocols are divided into four classes:</p>

<dl>
<dt>outer</dt>
<dd>protocols which may only occur at the very beginning of the
document; only <code>#basket:</code> may occur in this location.</dd>
<dt>start</dt>
<dd>protocols which may occur at the start of a text; only
<code>#atf:</code>, <code>#bib:</code>, <code>#link:</code>,
<code>#note:</code> and <code>#version:</code> may occur in this
location.</dd>
<dt>after</dt>
<dd>protocols which may occur only after all other protocols have been
given in a particular section; only <code>#note:</code> may occur in
this location.  Other protocols are not required before
<code>#note:</code>, but if they are present they must precede
it.</dd>
<dt>inter</dt>
<dd>protocols which may occur between lines of a text; only
<code>#bib:</code>, <code>#lem:</code>, <code>#note:</code> and
<code>#var:</code> may occur in this location.</dd>
</dl>

<pre class="cookbook">#bib: MSL 14, 343

1. a
#lem: a[water]
#note: This can only occur after any protocols other than #note:.
</pre>
<esp:sh><esp:bookmark id="atf"/>#atf:</esp:sh>
<p>Introduces directives to the ATF processor. Implemented directives
are:</p>
<dl>

<dt><code class="example">lang &lt;LANG></code></dt>
<dd><p>Sets the default language for the text;  see under <esp:link page="gdltut" bookmark="sh_languages">languages in the GDL tutorial</esp:link> for more
information.</p>
<pre class="cookbook">
#atf: lang qpc
</pre></dd>

<!-- <dt><code class="example">script &lt;SCRIPT></code></dt>
<dd><p>Sets the default script for the text; see under <a
href="../GDL/gdltut.html#scripts">scripts in the GDL tutorial</a> for more
information.</p>
<pre class="cookbook">
#atf: script 2</pre></dd> -->

<dt><code class="example">use &lt;FEATURE></code></dt>
<dd><p>The <code>use</code> directive enables <esp:link page="advanced">less commonly used ATF
features</esp:link>, which are turned off by default, to be turned on.
<code>FEATURE</code> must be one of: alignment-groups; legacy; lexical; math;
mylines.</p>
<pre class="cookbook">
#atf: use lexical
</pre></dd>

</dl>

<esp:sh><esp:bookmark id="basket"/>#basket:</esp:sh>
<p>This protocol is used only by the CDLI ATF repository system; the
content is a token used internally by the repository and should not be
changed by users.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:bookmark id="bib"/>#bib:</esp:sh>
<p>Bibliography information my be included using this protocol and may
then be included with locator strings to provide text and publication
information, e.g.:</p>
<pre class="cookbook">
&amp;P312111 = Some Lexical Text
1. a
#bib: MSL 14, 33</pre>

<p>It could be rendered as: <code>(Some Lexical Text 1 [MSL 14,
33])</code> but is not currently implemented.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:bookmark id="lem"/>#lem:</esp:sh>
<p>Gives lemmatization for the line before.  The format is a list of
lemmata separated by semi-colon-space (<code>; </code>) and the number
of lemmata must equal the number of words in the lemmatized line:</p>
<pre class="cookbook">
1. a i3-nag
#lem: a[water]; naj[drink]</pre>

<esp:sh><esp:bookmark id="lemmatizer"/>#lemmatizer:</esp:sh>
<p>Introduces directives to the lemmatization subsystem.  Implemented
directives are:</p>

<dl>
<dt><code class="example">sparse do &lt;FIELDS></code></dt>
<dd>Enables selective lemmatization which is useful for texts where
not all fields have been (or can be) lemmatized.  The
<code>&lt;FIELDS></code> must match field names used in the
document.  See the lexical documentation for an example.</dd>
</dl>

<esp:sh><esp:bookmark id="link"/>#link:</esp:sh>
<p>Introduces directives to the linkage subsystem.  Implemented
directives are:</p>

<dl>
<dt><code class="example">def &lt;SYMBOL> = &lt;ID> = &lt;NAME></code></dt>
<dd><p>Defines a SYMBOL to refer to the text indicated by ID and NAME;
interlinear links can then refer to the text via the symbol (see the
linkage documentation for more information and examples):</p>
<pre class="cookbook">
&amp;P123321 = Some Exemplar
#link: def A = Q000002 = Archaic Lu A
1. NAMESZDA
>> A 1
</pre>
</dd>
</dl>

<esp:sh><esp:bookmark id="note"/>#note:</esp:sh>
<p>Notes given using this protocol are included in the rendered ATF text.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:bookmark id="syntax"/>#syntax:</esp:sh>
<p>Introduces directives to the syntax processing subsystem.  Implemented directives are:</p>
<dl>
<dt><code>line_is_unit</code></dt>
<dd>Instructs the unit-processor to treat each line as a unit by
default.  This protocol is automatically emitted when <code>#atf: use
lexical</code> is given.</dd>
</dl>

<esp:sh><esp:bookmark id="var"/>#var:</esp:sh>
<p>Informal annotation of text variants; see the composites
documentation for a more structured implementation.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:bookmark id="version"/>#version:</esp:sh>
<p>Provides a location in the ATF file for a version number or version
control system string.</p>

<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>
</body>
</html>
</esp:page>
