<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
        xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
   xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
   >

  <esp:name>P4 URL Tester</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Test Page for P4 URLs</esp:title>

  <html><head></head><body>

  <p>This page combines examples of P4 URLs with test links to verify
  that they are working.</p>

  <esp:sh>Pager</esp:sh>

  <p>The entry point to a project corpus is the [PROJECT]/pager link:
  <esp:link class="demo"
  url="/rimanum/pager">/rimanum/pager</esp:link></p>

  <p>The default list is <code>outlined.lst</code> and does not need
  to be included in the URL. The next few examples use the default
  list to illustrate zooming and paging.</p>

  <p>To go to the second page use page=2 in the QUERY_STRING:
  <esp:link class="demo"
	    url="/rimanum/pager">/rimanum/pager?page=2</esp:link>.</p>

  <p>To select a group using the zoom menu, the pager uses the index
  in the list of group options, e.g., zoom=2 in the QUERY_STRING:
  <esp:link class="demo"
	    url="/rimanum/pager?zoom=2">/rimanum/pager?zoom=2</esp:link></p>

  <p>When zoom is non-zero the pager first selects the zoom-group and
  then selects the requested page within that group.</p>

  <p>To use a list other than the default specify list= in the
  QUERY_STRING: <esp:link class="demo"
  url="/rimanum/pager?list=withlem&amp;page=2">/rimanum/pager?list=withlem&amp;page=2"</esp:link>.</p>

  <p>For selecting pager items, normally text editions, see <esp:link
  bookmark="h_items">the Items section below</esp:link>.</p>

  <esp:sh>Glossaries</esp:sh>

  <p>A glossary is selected by appending the glossary language string
  to the URL: <esp:link class="demo"
  url="/rimanum/sux">/rimanum/sux</esp:link></p>

  <p>In glossaries, the zoom menu consists of the letter sections the
  glossary has--unlike pager zoom items they are named with the
  letter: <esp:link class="demo"
  url="/rimanum/sux?zoom=M">/rimanum/sux?zoom=M</esp:link>.</p>

  <p>In glossaries the selected item is a glossary article, see <esp:link
  bookmark="h_items">the Items section below</esp:link>.</p>

  <p>Glossary articles contain instance lists, for which see <esp:link
  bookmark="h_instances">the Instances section below</esp:link>.</p>

  <esp:sh>Instances</esp:sh>

  <p>Instances are references that record the occurrence of a word or
  key. Instances can prepackaged in the glossary, or from search
  results, or from static lists. Instance references are most often to
  words, but may also be to catalogue entries or glossary
  articles.</p>

  <p>Glossary instances are treated like lists with the special
  QUERY_STRING option xis: <esp:link class="demo"
  url="/rimanum/sux?xis=sux.r000002">/rimanum/sux?xis=sux.r00002</esp:link>.</p>

  <p>Search instances are lists with the special prefix
  <code>s.</code>: <esp:link class="demo"
  url="/rimanum?list=s.12e2f6">/rimanum?list=s.12e2f6</esp:link>.</p>
  
  <esp:sh>Items</esp:sh>

  <p>Items are most often either text editions or glossary
  articles. They configure their own zoom and page settings, and the
  item is given at the end of the URL rather than in the QUERY_STRING.</p>

  <p>A text instance is a PQX-name after the project URL: <esp:link
  class="demo" url="/rimanum/P405120">/rimanum/P405120</esp:link>.</p>

  <p>A glossary article instance is an OID after the project/glossary
  URL: <esp:link class="demo"
  url="/rimanum/sux/x0000002">/rimanum/sux/x0000002"</esp:link>.</p>
  
</body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
