<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

<esp:name>Fonts</esp:name>
<esp:title>Unicode fonts for Oracc</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>

<p class="firstpara">This page provides access to a variety of Unicode fonts for transliteration and normalisation, as well as for cuneiform script. </p>





<esp:h>Unicode Transliteration Fonts</esp:h>

<p>Fonts are only referenced here if they are both free and include
the full set of Unicode characters needed for Assyriological
transliterations as listed on
the <esp:link page="visitor-unicode">Unicode for Cuneiform
Transliteration</esp:link> page.  All Oracc fonts are released under the
terms of the <esp:link url="http://scripts.sil.org/OFL/">SIL Open Font
License</esp:link>.</p>

<p>If you need additional characters please let the Oracc steering committee know.</p>

<p>For daily work the best fonts to try are Ungkam Basic
and DejaVu.  Ungkam has two forms, the Basic and the Book Basic, with
the Basic being better for on-screen use and the Book Basic being 
better for print.  DejaVu is useful to have as well, because it has
sans-serif and monospaced fonts.</p>

<esp:sh>Ungkam</esp:sh>

<p>Ungkam may be the first calque from Latin into Sumerian; the fonts
are modified as permitted from Victor Gaultney's
beautiful <esp:link url="http://scripts.sil.org/gentium_download/">"Gentium"
typefaces</esp:link>.</p>

<h3>Ungkam Basic</h3>

<p>This is a version of the Gentium Basic and Gentium Book Basic
families in which all fonts have been extended to meet the
requirements above.</p>  

<ul>
<li>Version for Mac OS 10.5 and earlier: <esp:link url="~/downloads/UngkamBasic-mac.zip">[Download here]</esp:link></li>
<li>Version for Windows, Unix and Mac OS 10.6: <esp:link url="~/downloads/UngkamBasic-ttf.zip">[Download here]</esp:link>.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Ungkam Original</h3>

<p>This is a version of the original, full Gentium font extended to
meet the requirements above and named Ungkam.  Version 1.2 is now
available.</p> 
<ul>
<li>Version for Mac OS 10.5 and earlier: <esp:link url="~/downloads/ungkam-1.2-mac.zip">[Download here]</esp:link></li>
<li>Version for Windows, Unix and Mac OS 10.6: <esp:link url="~/downloads/ungkam-1.2-ott.zip">[Download here]</esp:link>.</li>
</ul>

<esp:sh>DejaVu</esp:sh>

<p>The extended version of Bitstream Vera, named Lynn, has been discontinued.
Instead we strongly recommend the excellent ongoing work to extend Vera under
the name <esp:link url="http://dejavu-fonts.org/">DejaVu Fonts</esp:link>.</p>

<ul>
<li>Version for Mac OS 10.5 and earlier: <esp:link url="~/downloads/DejaVu-mac.zip">[Download here]</esp:link></li>
<li>Version for Windows, Unix and Mac OS 10.6: <esp:link url="~/downloads/DejaVu-ttf.zip">[Download here]</esp:link>.</li>
</ul>


<esp:sh>Freefont</esp:sh>

<p>An extended version of the FreeFont project's 2009-01-04 release.
  Minimally tested.</p>
<ul>
<li>Version for Mac OS 10.5 and earlier: <esp:link url="~/downloads/FreeFont-mac.zip">[Download here]</esp:link></li>
<li>Version for Windows, Unix and Mac OS 10.6: <esp:link url="~/downloads/FreeFont-ttf.zip">[Download here]</esp:link>.</li>
</ul>


<esp:sh>Desconsolata</esp:sh>

<p>An experimental font based on <esp:link url="http://www.levien.com/type/myfonts/inconsolata.html">Ralph
Levien's Inconsolata</esp:link>, available in monospaced version only and
intended for limited on-screen use.  The font includes some
superscript characters in the Private Use Area to support aligning
text matrices on-screen even when they include determinatives.  This
font is distributed only in TrueType format.</p> 

<ul>
<li><esp:link url="~/downloads/Desconsolata-ttf.zip">[Download here]</esp:link>.</li>
</ul>

<esp:h>Cuneiform Fonts</esp:h>

<esp:sh>CuneiformNA</esp:sh>

<p>A font based on original MetaFont/Type1 fonts by <esp:link url="http://www-hep2.fzu.cz/~piska/cuneiform.html">Karel Píška</esp:link>
with Neo-Assyrian sign-forms.</p>

<ul><li><esp:link url="~/downloads/CuneiformNA.zip">[Download here]</esp:link></li></ul>

<esp:sh>CuneiformOB</esp:sh>

<p>A font based on Cuneiform Composite whose forms are closer to
those found in Old Babylonian monumental and literary texts.</p>

<ul><li><esp:link url="~/downloads/CuneiformOB.zip">[Download here]</esp:link></li></ul>


<esp:sh>Cuneiform Composite</esp:sh>

<p>This is the official font of the book, soon to be a major movie.
It was created and is maintained by Steve Tinney.  Alphabetician
and font designer Michael Everson of <esp:link url="http://www.evertype.com/">Evertype</esp:link> corrected many glyph
problems.</p>

<p>This is a composite font which is based on Ur III forms but which
ranges from Fara to Neo-Assyrian in its outliers.  The reason for this
is that it was designed to cover all of the cuneiform defined in
Unicode version 5.0.  For PDFs of the Unicode 5.0 code pages see
<esp:link url="http://www.unicode.org/charts/">the Unicode web site</esp:link>.</p>

<p>It is anticipated that subsequent development of CuneiformComposite
will improve the relative sizes of signs and fix any remaining glyph
errors.</p>

<p>CuneiformComposite is released under the terms of
the <esp:link url="http://scripts.sil.org/OFL/">SIL Open Font License</esp:link>.</p>

<p>After you install the font, you can test-drive it by viewing the following pages:</p>
<blockquote><p>
<esp:link page="cuneitab_0">Unicode Cuneiform Table page 1</esp:link><br/>
<esp:link page="cuneitab_1">Unicode Cuneiform Table page 2</esp:link><br/>
<esp:link page="cuneitab_2">Unicode Cuneiform Table page 3</esp:link><br/>
<esp:link page="cuneitab_3">Unicode Cuneiform Table page 4</esp:link><br/>
<esp:link page="cuneitab_4">Unicode Cuneiform Table page 5</esp:link>
</p></blockquote>

<ul><li><esp:link url="~/downloads/CuneiformComposite-1001.zip">[Download here]</esp:link></li></ul>


<esp:h>Other Non-Latin Fonts</esp:h>
<esp:sh>Aegean</esp:sh>

<p>Aegean is a free font created by George Douros which supports Old
Persian, Ugaritic, and other scripts relevant to ancient Near Eastern
research.  You can download a locally cached
copy of the distribution here, or go to its <esp:link url="http://users.teilar.gr/~g1951d/">home page here</esp:link>.</p>

<ul><li><esp:link url="~/downloads/Aegean.zip">[Download here]</esp:link></li></ul>

<esp:h>Installation Instructions</esp:h>

<p>First download the ZIP file containing the font from the
<code>[Download here]</code> link (you may need to control-click to save it
rather than open it in your browser window) and unzip the font.</p>

<p>System-specific font-installation procedures vary—additional
installation hints for systems not covered below are welcome.</p>

<dl>
<dt>Mac OS X</dt>
<dd>Double click on the font to open it in Fontbook and click on
Install; for 10.6 use the TrueType (.ttf) fonts, <b>NOT</b> the Mac
downloads.</dd>
<dt>Linux</dt>
<dd>For Redhat EL 3 simply copy the font (as superuser) to /usr/share/fonts.</dd>
<dt>Windows</dt>
<dd>For Windows
see <esp:link url="http://support.microsoft.com/kb/314960/">these
cookbook instructions</esp:link>.</dd>
</dl>

<esp:h>System-specific Hints</esp:h>

<esp:sh>Use ClearType on Windows XP</esp:sh>

<p>If you are using Windows XP, you will benefit from enabling
ClearType (which is enabled by default on Vista).  Instructions for
doing this are available from <esp:link url="http://support.microsoft.com/kb/306527/">this MS page</esp:link>.</p>


<esp:sh>Mac OS 10.6 and higher</esp:sh>

<p>As of 10.6/Snow Leopard the <code>.dfont</code> format is no longer used; be
sure to use the normal TrueType (.ttf) files.</p>

<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>

</body></html></esp:page>
