<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

<esp:name>Glossaries</esp:name>
<esp:title>Using the Oracc glossaries</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>
<p class="firstpara">Most Oracc corpora are at least partially lemmatised; that is, the words in them are tagged in order to generate language glossaries. An Oracc corpus usually has more than one glossary (for instance Akkadian, Sumerian, Names) but they all work in essentially the same way. This page describes how to use them.</p>

<p><esp:link bookmark="h_accessingaprojectsglossaries">Accessing glossaries</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_whatyousee">What you see</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_header">Header</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_outlinepane">Outline Pane</esp:link> | <esp:link bookmark="h_mainpane">Main Pane</esp:link></p>

<esp:h>Accessing a project's glossaries</esp:h>
<p>You can access a project's or corpus's glossaries by one of two routes:</p>
                         
<ul>
<li>The <esp:link page="visitor-userguide"
bookmark="h_glossaries">Glossaries list</esp:link> on the <esp:link page="visitor-userguide"
bookmark="h_theprojecthubpage">Hub Page</esp:link> of
a project takes you to the home page of each glossary. From there you can browse or
search the entire glossary. </li>
<li>In <esp:link page="visitor-userguide" bookmark="h_textitemmode">Text Item Mode</esp:link>, each transliterated word in the corpus may be linked
to a glossary entry. When you place your cursor over the word, the outline
entry pops up; and when you click on the word you are taken to the <esp:link bookmark="h_fullglossaryentries">full entry</esp:link>.</li>
</ul>

      
<esp:h>What you see</esp:h>

<p>When you go to the front page of an Oracc glossary, you will see the screen split into three parts:</p>
<ul>
    <li>the coloured <esp:link bookmark="h_header">header</esp:link> at the top;</li>
    <li>the  <esp:link bookmark="h_outlinepane">outline pane below it</esp:link>, to the left;</li>
    <li>and the  <esp:link bookmark="h_mainpane">main pane</esp:link> in the centre of the screen.
</li>
</ul>
<p>The contents of the header and outline pane stay mostly the same as you move through the glossary. The contents of the main pane change, though, depending on your actions in the header and outline pane.</p>

<esp:sh>Header</esp:sh>
<p>You can use the coloured header at the top of the screen to
navigate your way around the glossary, and to perform searches. It is
divided into three different zones, from left to right and top to bottom:</p>
<ul>
<li>the same <esp:link page="visitor-userguide" bookmark="h_thenavigationzone">navigation zone</esp:link> as in the main corpus, for moving to different parts of the website;</li>
<li>the usual <esp:link page="visitor-userguide" bookmark="h_thesearchzone">search zone</esp:link>, for finding signs, words and phrases; but now it will search only in this particular glossary;</li>
<li>and in some contexts you will also see the <esp:link
page="visitor-userguide" bookmark="h_thepagerzone">pager
zone</esp:link>, for paging through different texts, catalogue
entries, and search results.</li>
</ul>


<esp:sh>Outline Pane</esp:sh>
<p>The left-hand outline pane lists the following items, which you can use to browse the glossary:</p>
<dl>
<dt>ALL</dt>
<dd>This links to a list of single-line <esp:link bookmark="h_outlineglossaryentries">summary entries</esp:link> for every item in the glossary.</dd>
<dt>the letters A-Z (or a subset of them)</dt>
<dd>Each of these gives you single-line <esp:link bookmark="h_summaryglossaryentries">summary entries</esp:link> for every item in the glossary with that initial letter.</dd>
<!-- <dt>One Big File</dt>
<dd>This gives you a complete listing of the <esp:link
bookmark="h_fullglossaryentries">full entries</esp:link> for the
entire glossary. </dd> -->
</dl>

<esp:h>Main Pane</esp:h>
<esp:sh>Summary Glossary Entries</esp:sh>
<p>You can access outline glossary entries via the Summaries or the indvidual letters in the <esp:link bookmark="h_outlinepane">Outline Pane</esp:link>, or by using the search box. An outline glossary entry looks like this:</p>
<blockquote><p><span class="example">ana [TO] PRP (2x) "for; to"</span></p></blockquote>
<p>It has five components:</p>
<dl>
<dt>Citation form (e.g., <span class="example">ana</span>)</dt>
<dd>The dictionary headword or lemma. Akkadian nouns are always given in the nominative singular (e.g., <span class="example">awīlu</span>) and verbs in the infinitive (e.g., <span class="example">alāku</span>), in an un-mimated form called <esp:link page="akk-anno" bookmark="h_citationformscf">Conventional Akkadian</esp:link>.</dd>
<dt>Guide word (e.g., <span class="example">[TO]</span>)</dt>
<dd>The basic translation.</dd>
<dt>Part of speech (e.g., <span class="example">PRP</span>)</dt>
<dd>Abbreviation such as N = noun, V = verb, PRP = preposition, AJ = adjective, AV = adverb. For more details see the documentation on <esp:link page="linganno" bookmark="h_replacingxs">lingusitic annotation</esp:link>.</dd> <!---->
<dt>Attestations (e.g., <span class="example">(2x)</span>)</dt>
<dd>The number of times this word occurs in the (lemmatised part of) the current corpus.</dd>
<dt>The context-based senses (e.g., <span class="example">"for; to"</span>)</dt>
<dd>The various context-based meanings of the word, as used in the current corpus. 
</dd>
</dl>
<p>Clicking on the coloured component of the outline entry will take you to
 the corresponding <esp:link bookmark="h_fullglossaryentries">full glossary entry</esp:link>. Depending on the context, it may appear in the main pane or in a pop-up window.</p>
<esp:sh>Full Glossary Entries</esp:sh>
<p>Full glossary entries look the same, whether they are in the main glossary pane or a pop-up window. They are divided into three parts:</p>
<ul>
<li>The top line is a summary, showing the citation form (dictionary headword or lemma), guide translation(s),
<esp:link page="linganno" bookmark="h_replacingxs">part(s) of speech</esp:link>, and number of instances in the online corpus. You can click on this number to see all the instances in context.</li>
<li>The next section shows periods, spellings (transliterations), and normalisations of all the
attestations in the corpus. For Sumerian words, it also shows their base forms and morphological forms. Click on any of these to see them shown in context. A pop-up window
will appear, showing the relevant lines of manuscript or composite text, with
the glossary word highlighted. You can then click on the coloured designation (publication number or composition name) to see the
whole transliteration and translation.</li>
<li>The third and final section lists the different meanings of the word within
the corpus, showing their relative frequencies. Click on any of the
frequencies to see the headwords in context.</li>
</ul>

<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>



</body></html></esp:page>
