<?xml version="1.0"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Glossaries</esp:name><esp:title>Glossaries</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <h2>Introduction</h2>
      <p>Glossaries in Oracc provide a place to collect information
      about words in a way that can be used by the lemmatizer to
      create an exhaustive index of words and forms in a corpus.  The
      formal name of the glossary type in Oracc is the Corpus-Based
      Dictionary, and the abbreviation CBD is often used in Oracc to
      refer to this type.</p>
      <p>An Oracc glossary consists of a brief header and a series of
      entries.  Each entry consists of a series of tags most of which
      have content that continues on the rest of the line.  Each tag
      must begin a new line, and blank lines are not allowed within
      entries.  When the content is too long to fit on one line
      comfortably, any tag may be continued onto one or more
      continuation lines.  Continuation lines must begin with one or
      more space characters.</p>
      <h2>Glossary Header</h2>
      <h2>Core Tags</h2>
      <h3>@entry ... @end entry</h3>
      <p>Each glossary article begins with an <code>@entry</code> tag.
      This gives the Citation Form (CF), Guide Word (GW) and
      Part-of-Speech (POS) for the word, in the form CF [GW] POS,
      i.e., the GW is in square brackets, and there is a space before
      the open bracket and after the close bracket. The CF [GW] POS
      must be unique within a glossary.</p>
      <p>The <code>@entry</code> tag may be preceded by characters
      from the ACD module, and may be followed by an exclamation
      mark, <code>!</code>, indicating priority, or an
      asterisk <code>*</code> indicating that the entry is a phrase
      consisting of a sequence of words which retain their own
      meanings. PSUs, sequences of words with a meaning distinct from
      the individual parts, are not marked with the asterisk.</p>
      <p>Each article must end with <code>@end entry</code> written on
      its own line.</p>
      <h3>@bases</h3>
      <p>The <code>@bases</code> tag is used to list the bases for
      Sumerian words.  Bases are separated by a semicolon
      (<code>;</code>), e.g., <code>du; du₃</code>.  Bases may be
      specified as a primary base with alternate transliterations of
      the base in parentheses, in whch case multiple alternate bases
      may be separated by a comma followed by a space
      (<code>, </code>), e.g., <code>sag₉ (sa₆, ša₆, šag₉)</code>.</p>
      <p>Stems can be associated with bases by giving the stem,
      preceded by an asterisk and followed by a space, immediately
      before a primary base, e.g., <code>*du du₇; *dudu
      du₇-du₇</code>.</p>
      <p>The ACD module also provided facilities for remapping an
      existing base to a new base.</p>
      <h3>@form</h3>
      <p>The <code>@form</code> tag links instances in the corpus to
      the entries in the glossary. The first element is always a
      written form as it might occur in the corpus but without any
      half, square, angle or round brackets.  Following the written
      form various elements may occur depending in part on the
      language of the corpus. These elements are always marked by one
      or more characters which indicate the type of the element. No
      space is allowed between the type character and the data
      element.</p>
      <dl>
      <dt>$ = NORM</dt>
      <dd>The normalized version of the writing. This varies by
      language: in Akkadian, for example, it is the transcription of
      the word-form, without hyphens and determinatives and with
      accents. This is not used in the source version of Sumerian
      glossaries because it can be computed from the morphology (see
      below).</dd>
      <dt>* = STEM</dt>
      <dd>The STEM, which may be a form of the BASE in Sumerian, or a
      notation such as D, Š, N, in Akkadian, or possibly other
      conventions for other languages.</dd>
      <dt>/ = BASE</dt>
      <dd>The BASE utilized in a Sumerian writing. This must match a
      base given in the <code>@bases</code> part of the entry.</dd>
      <dt>+ = CONT</dt>
      <dd>The Sumerian grapheme following the base, used only when that
      grapheme is the continuation of the end of the BASE,
      e.g., <code>-ma</code> in <code>inim-ma</code>.  The
      deconstruction of the grapheme gives the consonant which
      continues the grapheme followed by the vowel which is normally a
      morpheme or morpheme constituent.</dd>
      <dt># = MORPH</dt>
      <dd>The morphology string for the writing.</dd>
      <dt>## = MORPH2</dt>
      <dd>The second morphology string for the writing.</dd>
      <dt>@ = RWS</dt>
      <dd>The RWS, Register or Writing System, for the form.</dd>
      <dt>COFs and PSUs</dt>
      <dd>Special rules apply to <code>@form</code> lines for COFs and
      PSUs, as described in the relevant pages.</dd>
      <dd>The <code>@form</code> tag may be followed by an exclamation
      mark, <code>!</code>, indicating priority.</dd>
      </dl>
      <h3>@sense</h3>
      <p>The <code>@sense</code> tag gives meanings for the word as
      well as a Part-of-Speech for the sense, which is the Effective
      Part-of-Speech (EPOS) in lemmatization.</p>
      <p>The <code>@sense</code> tag may be preceded by characters
      from the ACD module, and may be followed by an exclamation
      mark, <code>!</code>, indicating priority.</p>
      <p>An optional (in fact, rarely given) guideword specific to the
      sense, or SGW, may follow the <code>@sense</code> tag in square
      brackets: this is used by the lemmatizer to provide a strict
      match when testing the inline sense for a match to the glossary
      sense.</p>
      <p>The first required element after the <code>@sense</code> tag
      is a valid Part-of-Speech.  After the POS comes the meaning for
      the sense.</p>
      <h3>@note</h3>
      <h3>@inote</h3>
      <h2>Additional Tags</h2>
      <h3>@equiv</h3>
      <h3>@isslp</h3>
      <h3>@bib</h3>
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
