<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
        xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
   xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
   >

  <esp:name>OIDs</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Oracc OIDS</esp:title>

  <html><head></head><body>

  <p><em>NOTE:</em> Oracc IDs are presently in development and are not
  (quite) suitable for external use as persistent IDs. This page will
  be updated when that stage is reached, probably in summer 2019.</p>

  <h2>Overview</h2>

  <p>Oracc provides unique, persistent IDs for sign list and glossary
  data and we call these Oracc IDs, or OIDs.  They are assigned
  internally by Oracc on only one of its machines, and are propagated
  from that machine to the other Oracc servers.  Only a few projects
  are allowed to request assignment of new OIDs, or other changes to
  OIDs such as retiring or redirecting them.  The general goal is to
  allow external projects to refer to Oracc words, senses, and signs
  in a way that is guaranteed to be both unique and permanent.</p>

  <h2>Quick Start Examples</h2>

  <p>Here are some fragments of the OIDs table--but note that the
  actual OIDs in this fragment are not yet guaranteed against
  changing:</p>

  <table style="width: 50%">
    <tr><td>o0000004</td><td>sl</td><td>1(DIŠ)</td><td>sign</td><td></td></tr>
    <tr><td>o0000005</td><td>sl</td><td>1(EŠE₃)</td><td>sign</td><td></td></tr>
    <tr><td>o0000006</td><td>sl</td><td>1(GEŠU)</td><td>sign</td><td></td></tr>
    <tr/>
    <tr><td>o0002851</td><td>sux</td><td>a[arm]N</td><td>word</td><td></td></tr>
    <tr><td>o0002852</td><td>sux</td><td>a[arm//arm]N'N</td><td>sense</td><td>o0002851</td></tr>
    <tr><td>o0002853</td><td>sux</td><td>a[arm//plow handle]N'N</td><td>sense</td><td>o0002851</td></tr>
  </table>

  <p>The ID is in the first column, then comes the DOMAIN--sl for
  signlist or sux for Sumerian--then the KEY, then a TYPE, sign, word,
  or sense, then an EXTENSION which is only given when type=sense.</p>
  
  <h2>Technical Details</h2>

  <p>OIDs work with the following elements: ID, DOMAIN, AUTHORITY, KEY, TYPE, EXTENSION.</p>

  <dl>
    <dt>ID</dt>
    <dd>ID consists of a leading lowercase 'o' followed by
    7 decimal digits.</dd>
    <dt>DOMAIN</dt>
    <dd>DOMAIN is the top-level
    area division of the data assigned OIDs.  At present there is a
    domain 'sl', for 'signlist', which covers Sumero-Akkadian
    Cuneiform, and a domain 'sux', for 'Sumerian'.  When additional
    languages are added into the OID system, their three-letter ISO
    codes will be used for their domain, e.g., akk, for Akkadian.</dd>
    <dt>AUTHORITY</dt>
    <dd>An AUTHORITY is an Oracc project which is
    allowed to make additions and corrections to an OID domain.  The
    authority for the signlist domain, 'sl', is the Oracc Global
    Signlist Project, or OGSL.  The authority for the Sumerian domain,
    'sux', is the electronic Pennsylvania Sumerian Dictionary, or
    ePSD2.</dd>
    <dt>KEY</dt><dd>A KEY is a string representation of
    the object assigned the ID. The form of the keys in an OID domain
    is dependent on the type of the object.</dd>
    <dt>TYPE</dt><dd>TYPE
    gives the type of an object within a domain.  For the 'sl' domain,
    TYPE is presently 'sign' and the KEY is the sign name as given in
    OGSL.  For language domains such as 'sux', TYPE is 'word' or
    'sense', and the KEY is a standard Oracc word or sense signature,
    i.e., for word it is CF[GW]POS; for sense it is
    CF[GW//SENSE]POS'EPOS.</dd>
    <dt>EXTENSION</dt>
    <dd>EXTENSION is only used at present for objects with type=sense.
    The content is the OID of the word to which the sense
    belongs.</dd>
  </dl>
</body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
