<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>


<esp:name>Emacs for ATF</esp:name>
<esp:title>Working with ATF in Emacs using atf-mode</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>

<p class="firstpara">An Emacs major mode is available which makes editing ATF files a
bit easier and gives access to the template generator and checker.</p>




<esp:h>Starting to use Emacs</esp:h>

<!-- <p>See the pages on <esp:link page="aquamacs">Aquamacs</esp:link> and <esp:link page="emacsw32">EmacsW32</esp:link> for some additional help on getting started with Emacs.</p> -->


<esp:h>Using ATF mode</esp:h>

<p>If you name your files using the extension <code>.atf</code>, Emacs
will automatically switch into ATF mode when you create a new file or
load an existing one.</p>

<p>If you name your files using another extension, for example
<code>.txt</code>, you can set the mode explicitly by typing Esc-x (escape
then x) and then entering <code>atf-mode</code> at the prompt.</p>

<p>You can now use the ATF menu to read the ATF mode help, which will
in turn tell you how to use the other menu items effectively.</p>

<esp:h>Creating New Transliterations</esp:h>

<ol>
<li><p>Use menu File Visit new file  to open a new file</p></li>
<li><p>If your new file does not have a <code>.atf</code> extension,
enter ATF mode manually</p></li>
<li><p>Enter a template specification in your new file; you can access
the template help from the ATF menu</p></li>
<li><p>When you have completed your template, select menu Create
Template</p></li>
<li><p>Review the block structure you have created; if is incorrect, use
the undo function to remove the block structure, edit the template
specification and recreate the template</p></li>
<li><p>When you are satisfied with your template, delete the template
specification</p></li>
</ol>

<esp:sh>Selective Views</esp:sh>

<p>As of 2009-05-04, atf-mode enables outline-minor-mode;
use the 'ATF mode help' item from the ATF menu and read the 'Selective
Display' section for more information.</p>

<esp:h>Using the Checker</esp:h>

<p>Although you can use the menu, there are two particularly useful
keystrokes for working with the checker:</p>

<dl>
<dt>C-c-C-c</dt>
<dd>This is control-c then control-c again.  This runs the checker and
displays the results in another window.</dd>
<dt>C-c-C-n</dt>
<dd>This is control-c then control-n.  This moves the cursor to the
next erroneous line in your ATF file (it is often easier to use this
key than C-x-`, which is the mainstream key-binding for the next-error
command.</dd>
</dl>


<esp:h>Using Tramp to Edit Files on a Server</esp:h>

<p>Emacs includes a package named <code>tramp</code> which can be used
to edit files on a remote machine.  This means that if you work on a
project which is hosted on <code>oracc.museum.upenn.edu</code> you can
keep the files there and edit them using Emacs.  When you save the
file it is saved back to the server.</p>

<p>Tramp is activated automatically when you type a filename that
starts with a forward slash (<code>/</code>).  Tramp filenames have
the following syntax:</p>

<pre class="example">
/&lt;USER&gt;@&lt;MACHINE&gt;:&lt;FILE&gt;
</pre>

<p>This works with directories, too, which can then be clicked on to
open files; and you can also use &lt;TAB&gt;-completion, so tramp will go
away and get the list of files that complete for you.</p>

<p>So, if you are part of a project named, say, <code>dcclt</code>,
and you have the DCCLT password, you can start by typing the Emacs
command to open a file:</p>

<pre class="cookbook">
C-x C-f
</pre>

<p>You'll get a prompt <code class="cookbook">Find file:</code> which
may have some filename or directory already there.  You can ignore
anything that may be there and type starting with the forward
slash:</p>

<pre class="cookbook">
/dcclt@oracc.museum.upenn.edu:00atf/&lt;TAB&gt;
</pre>

<p>You should be prompted for a password and then see a list of the
sources.  Click on a file to open it.</p>


<esp:h>Troubleshooting</esp:h>

<esp:sh>Checker fails on Windows with strange '&amp;amp;P123456' results</esp:sh>

<p>Check the XML-RPC Customization option 'Xml Rpc Allow Unicode
String': if it is not set to 'nil', then set it to 'nil' and try
again.</p>

<p>(To find this option, try <code>Options -&gt; Customize Emacs -&gt; Settings
Matching Regexp</code> and type <code>xml-rpc-*</code> at the prompt.)</p>

<esp:sh>Using a Remote Access Program, e.g., HummingBird</esp:sh>

<p>If you are having difficulty connecting via a graphical user
interface to SSH and friends, check that all of the following are
correct:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Hostname = <code>oracc.museum.upenn.edu</code></p></li>
<li><p>Port number = 80</p></li>
<li><p>User ID = your project's abbreviation, in lowercase letters</p></li>
<li><p>Password = the correct password for your project</p></li>
<li><p>Starting Directory = the path <code>/home/</code> followed by your
project's abbreviation, in lowercase letters.</p></li>
</ul>


<esp:h>Entering Unicode Characters</esp:h>

<p>The Emacs ATF package includes an input method which is based on
the Emacs MULE TeX input method but adds some characters which are
useful for cuneiform transliterations.  If the ATF mode package is
installed correctly this input method is available under the name
'Cuneiform'.</p>

<p>To use this input method:</p>
<ol>

<li><p>Use control-backslash (<code>\</code>) to switch the Cuneiform input method on and off; when the method is enabled you will see a backslash at the left end of the status line</p></li>
</ol>


<esp:sh>Keyboard Sequences in Cuneiform Input Method</esp:sh>

<p>The Cuneiform transliteration input method is based on control
sequences used by the typesetting package TeX, with some additions.
In general these sequences start with the backslash character,
followed by an accent character, then the character that will receive
the accent.  These sequences are notated as, e.g., <code>\-v-s</code>
in the following table (meaning, in this case, that you type the
backslash, then v, then s, which gives you shin, š).</p>

<p>Note that the table below restricts the list of available
characters to those needed for cuneiform transliteration; many more
characters are available following the same principles.</p>

<p>See also <esp:link page="visitor-unicode">the Unicode for cuneiform
transliteration</esp:link> page and <esp:link page="visitor-fonts"> the fonts page</esp:link>.
If you don't see the subscript x character you probably need to update
to the latest fonts.</p>

<table class="pretty">
<tr>
<td>Sequence</td>
<td>Accent Name</td>
<td>Available for:</td>
<td>Results:</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>\-'</td><td>Acute</td><td>aeiuAEIUsS</td><td>áéíúÁÉÍÚśŚ</td></tr>
<tr><td>\-`</td><td>Grave</td><td>aeiuAEIU</td><td>àèìùÀÈÌÙ</td></tr>
<tr><td>\-=</td><td>Macron</td><td>aeiuAEIU</td><td>āēīūĀĒĪŪ</td></tr>
<tr><td>\-^</td><td>Circumflex</td><td>aeiuAEIU</td><td>âêîûÂÊÎÛ</td></tr>
<tr><td>\-v</td><td>Hachek</td><td>sS</td><td>šŠ</td></tr>
<tr><td>\-d</td><td>Dot-under</td><td>sStT</td><td>ṣṢṭṬ</td></tr>
</table>

<p>Several other characters are provided using the following sequences:</p>

<table class="pretty">
  <tr><td>\-h , \-H</td><td>ḫ , Ḫ</td></tr>
<tr><td>\-j , \-J</td><td>ŋ , Ŋ</td></tr>
<tr><td>\-[ , \-]</td><td>˹ , ˺</td></tr>
<tr><td>\-_[ , \-_]</td><td>⸤ , ⸥</td></tr>
</table>

<p>(Note that lower left/right square brackets are not used in ATF;
they are provided for use in citing published work.)</p>

<p>A few characters require typing a word after the backslash:</p>

<table class="pretty">
<tr><td>\times</td><td>×</td></tr>
<tr><td>\alef</td><td>ʾ</td></tr>
<tr><td>\ayin</td><td>ʿ</td></tr>
</table>

<p>If you are using the <code>#atf: use unicode</code> protocol you
must also type the grapheme index numbers as Unicode subscripts using
the <code>\-&lt;digit&gt;</code> sequences:</p>

<table class="pretty">
<tr><td>\-0</td><td><sub>0</sub></td></tr>
<tr><td>\-1</td><td><sub>1</sub></td></tr>
<tr><td colspan="2">...</td></tr>
<tr><td>\-9</td><td><sub>9</sub></td></tr>
<tr><td>\-+</td><td><sub>+</sub></td></tr>
<tr><td>\-x</td><td><sub>x</sub></td></tr>
</table>



<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:author first-names="Greta" last-name="Van Buylaere"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>

</body></html></esp:page>
