<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

<esp:name>Nisaba and Emacs</esp:name>
<esp:title>Using Nisaba or Emacs for Oracc work</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>
<p class="firstpara">Nisaba is a cuneioform text editor plug-in, written especially
for Oracc by <esp:link url="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/advanced-research-computing/advanced-research-computing-centre">UCL's Advanced Research Computing Centre</esp:link>, that enables all content creators to edit ATF files within the open-source editor <esp:link url="https://code.visualstudio.com">Visual Studio Code</esp:link>. With Nisaba, you can edit multiple texts at a time and produce translations in both left-to-right scripts such as the western alphabet and right-to-left scripts such as many modern Middle Eastern ones. You can also use it to edit project glossaries and write ESP portals. We now recommend Nisaba as our preferred editor. However, as some colleagues still use Emacs, we have kept our help pages for that code editor here too.</p>

<p>On these pages we discuss:</p>

<dl>
  <dt><esp:link page="nammu">Working with Nisaba</esp:link></dt>
  <dd>Here we link to the Github pages on how to install and set up Nisaba, and how to edit ATF files with it. We also recommend a workflow using Nisaba (in Visual Studio Code) and Github Desktop.</dd>
<dt><esp:link page="emacssetup">Preparing to work with Emacs</esp:link></dt>
<dd>On this page we describe how to obtain, install and configure it for Oracc work.</dd>
<!--<dt><esp:link page="aquamacs">Starting to use Aquamacs (Emacs for Mac)</esp:link></dt>
<dd>Here we give a short description of some features that we have found useful for editing and lemmatising ATF in Aquamacs (Emacs for Mac), apart from those provided by atf-mode.</dd>-->
<dt><esp:link page="emacsw32">Starting to use EmacsW32 (Emacs for PC)</esp:link></dt>
<dd>Here we give a short description of some features that we have found useful for editing and lemmatising ATF in EmacsW32 (Emacs for Windows), apart from those provided by atf-mode.</dd>
<dt><esp:link page="emacsuse">Working with ATF in Emacs using atf-mode</esp:link></dt>
<dd>An Emacs major mode is available which makes editing ATF files a bit easier and gives access to the template generator and checker.</dd>
</dl>
<p>See also the pages on <esp:link page="projemacs">managing projects with Emacs</esp:link> and <esp:link page="esp">building ESP portals</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>
</body></html></esp:page>
