<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

<esp:name>Nammu</esp:name>
<esp:title>Working with Nammu</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>
<p class="firstpara">Nammu is a simple text editor, written especially
for Oracc by <esp:link url="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/research-it-services/research-software-development">UCL's Research Development Software Group</esp:link>, that enables all content creators to edit ATF files, one
file at at time. </p>


<p>On this page we discuss:</p>

<ul>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="install">How to install Nammu</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="shortcuts">Keyboard shortcuts</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="create">How to create and save ATF files with Nammu</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="edit">How to edit ATF files with Nammu</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="validate">How to validate and lemmatise ATF
  files with Nammu</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="settings">How to change Nammu's settings</esp:link></li>
  <li><esp:link bookmark="report">How to report bugs and request improvements</esp:link></li>
</ul>


<esp:h><esp:bookmark name="install"/>How to install and set up
Nammu</esp:h>

<p>It's really easy to install Nammu:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Follow <esp:link url="https://github.com/oracc/nammu/releases"
  name="Oracc Nammu releases">this link to the Github Nammu downloads
  page</esp:link>.</li>
  <li>Double-click on the name of the latest release of Nammu, which
  will have a name like <span
  class="cookbook">nammu-0.7.0.jar</span>.</li>
  <li>Save the download to wherever you want it to live on your own
  computer.</li>
  <li>Open it by double-clicking on the Nammu icon. </li>
</ol>

<esp:sh>Troubleshooting</esp:sh>
<ul>
  <li><p>If you are running a Mac, your security settings may not let you
  open Nammu the first time after you install it. If that
  happens, go to your System Preferences and open "Security &amp;
  Privacy" in the top row of icons. Under the
  "General" tab, choose "Open anyway". Close your System Preferences
  and open Nammu.</p></li>
  <li><p>If you try to open Nammu and it doesn't work, it might be that you don't have Java installed. You can check if you do by <esp:link>opening a terminal</esp:link> and typing:</p>

<p class="cookbook">java</p>

<p>If that command is not recognised, then you'll need to download and
install the Java Runtime Environment (JRE). You can find the
appropriate JRE installable file for your operating system <esp:link url="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/jre8-downloads-2133155.html">here</esp:link>.</p>

<p>If you keep having trouble, you can also run it from the command line, like this:</p>

<p class="cookbook">java -jar /path/to/nammu.jar</p>

<p>(where you replace <span class="cookbook">/path/to</span> with the
actual file hierarchy in which your copy of Nammu lives. This will output a clearer log message about what the problem is.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>If you're an advanced user, and want to edit Nammu's configuration
file, read the instructions <esp:link
url="https://github.com/oracc/nammu#nammus-configuration-for-advanced-users"
rel="external" name="Nammu's configuration for advanced users">on Github</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark name="shortcuts"/>Keyboard shortcuts</esp:h>
<p>We hope you will find Nammu very easy intuitive to use. Explore the
items in the five drop-down menus, and hover your cursor over the
icons at the top of the Nammu window to see what they do. In addition
you can use these keyboard shortcuts:</p>

<table class="pretty">
<tr><th>Action</th> 	<th>Keystroke</th></tr>
<tr><th>New File</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + N</th></tr>
<tr><th>Open File</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + O</th></tr>
<tr><th>Close File</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + W</th></tr>
<tr><th>Save As</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + E</th></tr>
<tr><th>Save File</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + S</th></tr>
<tr><th>Validate</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + D</th></tr>
<tr><th>Lemmatise</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + L</th></tr>
<tr><th>Undo</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + Z</th></tr>
<tr><th>Redo</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + Y</th></tr>
<tr><th>Find</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + F</th></tr>
<tr><th>Find next</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + G</th></tr>
<tr><th>Replace all</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + A</th></tr>
<tr><th>Replace one</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + R</th></tr>
<tr><th>Show Help</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + H</th></tr>
<tr><th>Split Editor Horizontally</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + .</th></tr>
<tr><th>Split Editor Vertically</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + ;</th></tr>
<tr><th>Syntax Highlight Switch</th> 	<th>Ctrl/Cmd + T</th></tr>

</table>

<p>If you're already used to editing ATF in Emacs, this should
all seem very familiar. If not, we give some more detailed help below.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark name="create"/>How to create and save files in
Nammu</esp:h>

<p>The current version of Nammu only works with files that are on your
own computer. You cannot create or save files direct to the Oracc
server. If you're used to doing that, we recommend instead that you
pull your files off Oracc before you start editing and then, at the
end of your session, upload edited
files back to Oracc. We describe how to do that <esp:link
page="projunix" bookmark="h_uploadingatfodsandcataloguefilestooracc">on a separate
page</esp:link> [which does not yet exist].</p>

<esp:sh>Creating a new ATF file</esp:sh>
<p>You can create a new file in Nammu with the File -> New menu
item, or by clicking the first icon in the toolbar, or by typing
<span class="cookbook">Ctrl/Cmd + N</span>. They all give the
same result: a new dialogue box headed "New ATF Template". If you don't want to use this
template, simply choose the "Leave blank"
option in the bottom centre and the dialogue box will disappear.</p>

<p>Assuming you do want to use the template, each of the
text boxes should be self-explanatory, but if not, the help icons on
the right will tell you what to do. The completed dialogue box should
look something like this:</p>

<blockquote><p>CDLI's ID: <span class="cookbook">&amp;P123445</span> =
<span class="cookbook">CT 165, pl. 9</span><br/>
Project: <span class="cookbook">saao</span> / <span
class="cookbook">saa72</span><br/>
Language: <span class="cookbook">Neo-Assyrian</span></p></blockquote>

 <p>Then choose "Create template".  Nammu will auto-fill the main
 editing window with the text that you entered, e.g.,:</p>

 <blockquote><p class="cookbook">&amp;P123445 = CT 165, pl. 9<br/>
#project: saao/saa72<br/>
 #atf: lang akk-x-neoass</p></blockquote>

<p>and will remember your choice of project and language for next
time. But you can overwrite Nammu's pre-selections at any time, either
in the dialogue box, or in the main editing window.</p>

<p>Nammu does not auto-save your files. Remember to save at regular
intervals, so that you don't accidentally lose data.</p>

<esp:sh>Saving files</esp:sh>
<p>When you save a file for the first time, Nammu will open a "Save"
dialogue box, just like any word processor, with all the usual
options.</p>

<p>When you name your file, remember that you:</p>
<ul>
 <li>MUST NOT use spaces: use underscore _ or a hypen - instead if you want</li>
 <li>MUST give your file name the extension
 <span class="cookbook">.atf</span>.</li>
</ul>

<p>If your filename doesn't obey these simple rules, your file
may not work properly with Nammu or with Oracc.</p>

<p>By default, Nammu will suggest you save files to the same
same place as Nammu itself. But you can choose a different
folder/directory with the "Settings" dialogue box. You'll find this
via the File menu, or the cog-wheel icon in the toolbar. Change your
"working directory" by clicking "Browse" and selecting the
folder/directory where you want to save (and open) your ATF files. You
can change this setting as often as you like.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark name="edit"/>How to edit ATF files in
Nammu</esp:h>

<p>We have designed Nammu to be quite intuitive to use. You can cut and
paste, find and replace, etc., just as in any text editor. Here are a
few things you might not know about:</p>

<dl>
<dt>Validating and lemmatising</dt>
<dd>Unlike Emacs, you don't have to save a file before you validate or
lemmatise it. But, as before, you can only lemmatise a valid file. So
fix any validation errors before you lemmatise. Click on an error
message in the console at the bottom of the window to go to it in the
main editing window.</dd>

<dt>Split screen</dt>
<dd>You can split the window, horizontally or vertically. Find these
options in the Window menu or in the <esp:link bookmark="shortcuts">keyboard shortcuts</esp:link>. This option is
particularly useful when you are translating and lemmatising at the
same time.</dd>
</dl>

<p>If you're
an advanced user of Emacs, you won't find every single editorial
feature that you're used to. If you're really missing something,
though, please <esp:link bookmark="report">put in a request</esp:link> for it.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark name="report"/>How to report bugs and request
improvements to Nammu</esp:h>

<p>If you
want to ask questions, report bugs, or request new features please
contact us by creating a <span class="cookbook">New Issue</span> with
the green button on Nammu's Github <esp:link
url="https://github.com/oracc/nammu/issues" name="Github Oracc/Nammu
Issues" rel="external">Issues page</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>
</body></html></esp:page>
