<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
<esp:name>Prerequisites</esp:name>
<esp:title>Oracc Prerequisites</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>
<p class="firstpara">This document lists the Oracc prerequisites,
the packages which should be installed prior to
installing the Oracc.</p>



<p>If you are not familiar with Unix installation procedures, there is a 
<esp:link page="basics">brief introduction here</esp:link>.</p>

<!-- <p><strong>FIRST READ THE <esp:link url="ports">PORTING NOTES</esp:link> FOR YOUR SYSTEM OR SIMILAR
SYSTEMS</strong>.</p> -->

<p>Now install the following, in this order:</p>

<dl>
<dt>Current versions of the GNU build tools:</dt>
<dd>
  <p><strong>Note that on Mac OS X it is best to try porting without
  updating these tools first as some of them (in particular libtool) have been
  adapted by Apple and the Gnu versions may not understand necessary linker options.</strong></p>
  <p>The following basic tools should be up to date and synchronized, in
this order:</p>
  <ul>
  <li>m4</li>
  <li>autoconf</li>
  <li>automake</li>
  <li>libtool</li>
  </ul>
</dd>

<dt>Gperf</dt>
<dd>Some distributions do not include, or even provide, gperf (I'm looking at you, RHEL6.0). Get the
sources from <esp:link url="http://www.gnu.org">the Gnu website</esp:link>, build and install it</dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://www.pcre.org">PCRE</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides regular expression support; there is a precompiled version of the library for windows which can be found via the PCRE home page</p></dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://expat.sourceforge.net">Expat</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides XML parsing and the utility program `xmlwf' which is a useful way of checking XML files for well-formedness.  An abbreviated version of expat is included in the cdl/tools/src to facilitate compilation of the ATF processor, but the latest full version should also be installed to provide xmlwf</p></dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://www.xmlsoft.org">LibXML/LibXSLT</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides XML parsing and XSLT transformation. Binary distributions are available for many systems</p></dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://cpan.perl.org">Perl LibXML packages</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>search for `XML::LibXML' and `XML::LibXSLT'.  <strong>LibXML/LibXSLT should be installed first</strong>.  The Perl packages have several dependencies so these must also be installed.  At the last installation the following packages were necessary (if packages are missing a diagnostic is generally issued, so it may be that there are more or different prerequisites for any given installation.:</p>
<ul>
<li>XML-LibXML</li>
<li>XML-LibXML-Common</li>
<li>XML-LibXML-Fixup</li>
<li>XML-LibXML-Iterator</li>
<li>XML-LibXML-XPathContext</li>
<li>XML-LibXSLT</li>
<li>XML-NamespaceSupport</li>
<li>XML-NodeFilter</li>
</ul>
</dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://www.davidashen.net/rnv.html">Rnv:</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides validation according to Relax/NG Schemas in compact syntax (the version used in all of the schema documentation).  A version of this is included in cdl/tools/src so it is not essential to install the full distribution.</p></dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://laurikari.net/tre">Tre</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides regular expression support for msort, so install it before building msort.</p></dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://www.public-software-group.org/utf8proc">Utf8proc</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides UTF8 support for msort, so install it before building msort.  TODO: include this in Oracc system distro because the build/installation is non-standard.  For now, use `make' to build, then move the libraries to /usr/lib and the .h file to /usr/include (or wherever is appropriate).</p></dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://billposer.org/Software/libuninum.html">Libuninum</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides unicode number handling support for msort, so install it before building msort.</p></dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://gmplib.org">Gnu MP</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides bignum handling for msort.</p></dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://billposer.org/Software/msort.html">Msort</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides sorting facilities used by Oracc programs including the glossary manager.</p></dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/colorer/">Colorer</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides source colourization for the XDF resources listings. TODO: my HRC definitions have some fixes and should be downloadable separately from the Oracc server.</p></dd>

<dt><esp:link url="http://hyperestraier.sourceforge.net">Hyper-Estraier</esp:link></dt>
<dd><p>provides the documentation search on the Oracc website.</p></dd>

</dl>

<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>


</body></html></esp:page>
