<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Schemas</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Oracc schemas</esp:title>

	<html>
		<head>
		
		</head>
		<body>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/cbd/1.0">CBD: Corpus-Based Dictionary</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>The CBD format is used for glossaries and lexicons.
  The architecture is designed to support the inclusion of arbitrary
  items of information tailored to the needs of different languages or
  types of name books.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/cbd/2.0">CBD: Corpus-Based Dictionary</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>The CBD format is used for glossaries and lexicons,
  and this document describes version 2 of the CBD, a.k.a., G2.
  The architecture is designed to support the inclusion of arbitrary
  items of information tailored to the needs of different languages or
  types of name books.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/cdf/1.0">CDF: CDL Document Format</esp:link></esp:sh><p>CDF is an XML format for representing a variety of
  document types from text transliterations to books.  The format
  combines narrative facilities with technical data types such as XTF
  data and corpus-based dictionaries.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0">ESP: Electrostatic Portal</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>ESP is a port of George MacKerron's Electrostatic
  website building software to Oracc.  It is used for the portal components of all Oracc projects.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/gdl/1.0">GDL: Grapheme Description Language</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>Grapheme Description Language for embedding in
  higher-order document types such as text editions and
  signlists.  A formal definition with RNC schema is given interwoven
  with the ATF conventions for representing each element in
  the schema.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/sl/1.0">SL: Sign Lists</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>Sign list source files are maintained as a simple
  plain text file with @-commands in the manner of Oracc
  glossaries. This document gives an simple overview of the SL
  commands.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/xcf/1.0">XCF: XML Configuration Files</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>XCF is an XML vocabulary for setting program
  configuration values; one day there will be a more user-friendly
  ASCII front end.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/xcl/1.0">XCL:  XML Chunks and Lemmas</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>XCL is the format used as a basis for linguistic
  annotation.</p>

<!-- <esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/xdf/1.0">XDF:
	  XML Documentation Format</esp:link></esp:sh><p>The XDF format is an XML vocabulary which blends
  special-purpose tags, RelaxNG, Dublin Core metadata, and XHTML to
  implement a literate XML programming environment for RelaxNG's
  compact syntax.  Because XDF formalizes the metadata component of
  the work and creates a TOC automatically, it is also useful for
  general purpose documentation.</p> -->

<esp:sh><esp:link url=".org/">XFF: XML Forms Files</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>This document contains a preliminary description of  the XFF data format.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/XMD/1.0">XMD: XML MetaData</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>XMD is a CDL subsystem which imports catalogs
  containing metadata concerning texts and compositions and creates an
  XML version of the data.  Some validation of the catalog content is
  performed and sort codes are generated and added to some fields.
  XMD also encompasses a keyset-generator to create keys for
  indexing.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/xse/1.0">XSE: XML Search Expressions</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>XSE is a schema for expressing the search
  expressions that are understood by the Oracc native search
  engine.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/xst/1.0">XST: XML Syntax Trees</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>XML Syntax Trees provide a generic vocabulary for
  expressing syntactic data which is based closely on XCES.  This
  document describes the CDL system-level support for XST, including
  the facilities in the ATF notation for expressing syntactic
  annotation.  Such annotations may range from isolated hints to a
  parser which generates the bulk of syntax trees automatically to
  complete syntax trees interwoven with lemmatization in the
  linguistic annotation layer of ATF.  The annotations themselves are
  language-specific and are described in separate
  documents.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/xtc/1.0">XTC: XML Text Corpus</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>XTC (besides being a tribute) is a very simple XML
  vocabulary which provides a list of texts on which downstream corpus
  processing can operate.  The principle is that further linguistic
  service processing does not need to know anything system-specific,
  enabling the higher-order tools to operate on a variety of source
  corpora.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/xtf/1.0">XTF:  XML Transliteration Format Version</esp:link></esp:sh><p>XTF is an XML format for describing the
  transliteration of cuneiform texts; it also encompasses facilities
  for other kinds of editions commonly used in cuneiform studies.</p>

<esp:sh><esp:link url="http://oracc.org/ns/xtr/1.0">XTR: XML Translations</esp:link></esp:sh>
<p>This document provides the RNG schema used by the
XML version of translations and explains implementation details useful
for programmers; if you are typing translations in ATF you don't need
to read this page.</p>

<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>

		</body>
	</html>

</esp:page>
