<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

<esp:name>Aramaic</esp:name>
<esp:title>ARC: Oracc Linguistic Annotation for Aramaic</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>

<p class="firstpara">This document provides an overview of
  language-specific annotation conventions for Aramaic used in
 Oracc.

</p>



<esp:h>Transliteration</esp:h>

<p>Aramaic is indicated by the language shift <code>%arc</code>;
following this language shift, the ATF processor recognizes a special
set of conventions adapted to alphabetic scripts, and a special
transliteration system particular to Aramaic. The transliteration
system is that of the Comprehensive Aramaic Lexicon, and this document
has benefited from e-mail discussions with Steve Kaufman, Director of
the CAL.</p>

<pre class="example">

) = aleph    b = beth       g = gimel      d = daleth     h = he
w = waw      z = zayin      x = heth       T = teth       y = yodh
k = kaph     l = lamedh     m = mem        n = nun        s = samekh
( = ayin     p = pe         c = tsade      q = qoph       r = resh
$ = shin     &amp; = sin        t = taw

</pre>

<p>This ASCII transliteration is converted on input to the following
Unicode characters:</p>

<pre class="example">
bgdhwzyklmnspqrt : themselves
)      ʾ
(      ʿ
T      ṭ
c      ṣ
$      š
x      ḥ
&amp;      ś
</pre>

<p>Words are separated by spaces.</p>

<esp:h>Editing Conventions</esp:h>

<p>Matching square brackets are used for broken material, a following
question mark for unclear letters and a following exclamation mark for
corrected letters.  Multiple alternative possible readings are
separated by slashes (e.g., <code>d/r</code>).</p>

<p>Within square brackets, broken segments of relatively certain
length are indicated by a period for each missing letter.</p>

<p>Broken segments of uncertain length are indicated by underscore
characters, e.g., <code class="cookbook">[...]br
[________________________]</code> indicates that in the first break 3
characters are missing, and in the second break a large but
indeterminate number of characters is missing.</p>

<p>Spaces should be used to terminate words in breaks; words may
contain dots and underscores indicating that they are partially
preserved, e.g., <code class="cookbook">[_____ _]br[_ _____]</code>.</p>

<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>

</body></html></esp:page>
