<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
<esp:name>Sumerian primer</esp:name>
<esp:title>Sumerian Lemmatization Primer</esp:title>
<html><head/><body>
<p class="firstpara">A very quick start to get you lemmatizing
  Sumerian texts with the minimum effort possible.</p>



<esp:h>Overview</esp:h>

<p>Sumerian lemmatization works by drawing information from four
places:</p>

<ul>
<li>New entries in the interlinear lemmatization in the file</li>
<li>The project glossary, <code>00lib/sux.glo</code></li>
<li>ePSD, from the development version which is searchable <esp:link url="http://oracc.museum.upenn.edu/epsd/cbd/sux">on oracc</esp:link></li>
<li>The morphological analyzer</li>
</ul>

<p>Sumerian uses the same basic parts of speech as Akkadian, but with
the addition of three important ones:</p>

<ul>
<li>MORPH: the morphological analysis</li>
<li>BASE: the base form of the dictionary word as it occurs in the
writing</li>
<li>CONT: a continuation grapheme, i.e., normally a sign whose
consonant is the same as the end of the citation form of the word, and
whose vowel is either non-functional or contributes to the post-verbal
morphology.</li>
</ul>


<esp:h>Principles</esp:h>

<p>As a matter of principle, it is best to do as little as possible
when lemmatizing Sumerian.  In the normal case, it is enough to
lemmatize with a citation form and a sense--all of the other
components will get filled in for you by either ePSD or the
morphological analyzer.</p>

<p>In particular, ePSD's approach to adjectives in Sumerian is that
almost all of them are simply verbs, whose nonfinite forms can be used
in a variety of ways including modifiers and participles.  We
generally do not tag these using the Extended POS (EPOS), even where a
word has more than one listed POS in ePSD.  For example, you can
lemmatize <code>nir</code> as <code>nir[lordly]</code> or
<code>nir[lord]</code> and the lemmatizer will find the right POS/EPOS
combination for you.</p>


<esp:author first-names="Steve" last-name="Tinney"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="osc@oracc.org"/>

</body></html></esp:page>
